<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Anglia liberata, or, The rights of the people of England, maintained against the pretences of the Scotish King, as they are set forth in an Answer to the Lords Ambassadors propositions of England. Which ansvver was delivered into the Great Assembly of the United Provinces at the Hague, by one Mac-Donnel, who entitles himself Resident for his Majesty, &amp;c. June 28/18 1651: and is here published according to the Dutch copy. Whereto is added a translation of certain animadversions upon the answer of Mac-Donnel. Written by an ingenious Dutch-man. As also an additional reply to all the pretended arguments, insinuations and slanders, set forth in the said Scotish answer written a while since by a private pen, and now presented to the publick.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 165 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75357</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3178</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E643_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18922</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860499</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860499</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112620</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75357)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112620)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 99:E643[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Anglia liberata, or, The rights of the people of England, maintained against the pretences of the Scotish King, as they are set forth in an Answer to the Lords Ambassadors propositions of England. Which ansvver was delivered into the Great Assembly of the United Provinces at the Hague, by one Mac-Donnel, who entitles himself Resident for his Majesty, &amp;c. June 28/18 1651: and is here published according to the Dutch copy. Whereto is added a translation of certain animadversions upon the answer of Mac-Donnel. Written by an ingenious Dutch-man. As also an additional reply to all the pretended arguments, insinuations and slanders, set forth in the said Scotish answer written a while since by a private pen, and now presented to the publick.</title>
                  <author>MacDonnell, William, Sir.</author>
                  <author>Ingenious Dutch-man.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 68 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. Newcomb [and Samuel Brown] for Richard Lowns, at the White Lion in Pauls Church-yard near the west end,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"An answer to the propositions made by the English Ambassadors .. Hagh, printed by Samuel Brown, English book-seller, 1651" and "Animadversions upon a certain Scottish answer" each have separate dated title page; pagination and register are continuous.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "October. 7.".</note>
                  <note>Identified as Wing M119 on UMI microfilm set "Early English Books, 1641-1700".</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in Cambridge University Library (Early English books) and the British Library (Thomason Tracts).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Foreign relations --  Netherlands --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  Foreign relations --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112620:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anglia Liberata,</hi> OR, THE RIGHTS Of the People of <hi>ENGLAND,</hi> MAINTAINED AGAINST the Pretences of the SCOTISH King, As they are ſet forth in an ANSWER TO THE <hi>LORDS AMBASSADORS PROPOSITIONS</hi> of ENGLAND. Which ANSVVER was delivered into the <hi>Great Aſſembly</hi> of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces</hi> at the <hi>Hague,</hi> by one MAC-DONNEL, who entitles himſelf <hi>Reſident for his Majeſty,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>June</hi> 28/18 1651: And is here publiſhed according to the <hi>Dutch</hi> Copy. <hi>WHERETO IS ADDED</hi> A TRANSLATION OF CERTAIN <hi>Animadverſions</hi> upon the <hi>Anſwer</hi> of <hi>Mac-Donnel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written by an ingenious <hi>Dutch-man. AS ALSO</hi> AN ADDITIONAL REPLY To all the pretended Arguments, Inſinuations and Slanders, ſet forth in the ſaid <hi>SCOTISH ANSWER Written a while ſince by a</hi> private Pen, <hi>and now preſented to the</hi> PUBLICK.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. Newcomb</hi> for <hi>Richard Lowns,</hi> at the White <hi>Lion</hi> in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard near the Weſt end, 1651.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:112620:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:112620:2"/>
            <head>The Publiſher to the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou haſt here <hi>firſt,</hi> the <hi>Anſwer</hi> of <hi>Mac-Donnel</hi> (whom in the <hi>Dutch</hi> they call <hi>Mac-Dowel</hi>) to the <hi>Propoſitions</hi> of our <hi>Engliſh Ambaſſadors,</hi> as it was delivered by him, in the <hi>Great Aſſembly</hi> of the <hi>United Provinces;</hi> which having been publiſhed beyond Sea in <hi>Dutch,</hi> and tranſlated ſince into an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Print, is here preſented to a more publick view, with a few Correctives added thereunto to prevent the poiſon. And therefore in the <hi>ſecond place,</hi> thou haſt alſo a Tranſcript of certain <hi>ANI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MADVERSIONS</hi> upon <hi>Mac-Donnel's Anſwer,</hi> written by an honeſt <hi>Dutchman</hi> in his own Language, and now tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe <hi>ANIMADVERSIONS</hi> are indeed very pithy, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent, and ingenious; but becauſe they are only the <hi>Hints</hi> of Things, and not <hi>Diſcourſes</hi> ſo drawn at full, as to convince ſuch as are not eaſily perſwaded of the Truth of matters in Controverſie; therefore it was thought fit in the <hi>third place,</hi> to bring up the Rear with an <hi>Additional Reply;</hi> partly to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſe the main points more fully; and partly, to touch upon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other particulars of <hi>Mac-Donnels Anſwer,</hi> wholly neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Dutch <hi>Animadvertor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The truth is, theſe Papers have lain by for ſome time, by reaſon of the late diſturbances, they having been all ready prepared for the <hi>Preſs</hi> before, except the latter part of the fourth Chapter of the <hi>Additional Reply,</hi> which was lickt up, upon the cloſe of this laſt grand determination of Affairs at <hi>Worceſter.</hi> Perhaps, ſome expreſſions therein touching the <hi>Power of the Sword,</hi> at the firſt ſight, may not pleaſe all; but that all may be pleaſed, let them know, the <hi>Rights of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> are no way wronged, as long as the <hi>Sword</hi> is aſſerted, and acknowledged to be in the hands of the Parliament; who by the <hi>Law of the Sword</hi> have ſo nobly over-turned the <hi>Law of the Prerogative,</hi> and recovered the good old Laws, Liberties, and Priviledges of the people. And whereas it is here inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured
<pb facs="tcp:112620:3"/>to prove our <hi>Engliſh Relation</hi> to the <hi>old Treaties</hi> made withour Neighbours of <hi>Holland;</hi> know the intent is not in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wiſe to court that Nation to maintain Amity, but onely to refell the futility of thoſe Arguments of the <hi>Royal Party,</hi> who pretend to prove, that by vertue of thoſe <hi>Treaties,</hi> the <hi>Dutch</hi> are tied ſtill to the <hi>late Kings Family,</hi> as if they ſtood radicated in full force, in the perſon of the preſent <hi>young Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tender.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If there be any fault then in the <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>Additionall Reply,</hi> it is only his preſumption, that a <hi>private Pen</hi> ſhould meddle with matters of a publick Import: But the heneſt <hi>Dutch</hi> man having ſhewn him the way, he could not chuſe but follow him, and lay hold upon this opportunity, throughly to canvaſſe the princpall Points, Parts, and Pretences, that paſs up and down by Tradition, to ſupport the cauſe and intereſt of the <hi>Common Enemy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Perhaps they may at preſent ſeem as dead to ſome, having been Thunder ſtrook by the late fatall blow at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and therefore this Piece by way of <hi>Reply,</hi> may be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed now alſo to be of the leſs uſe and conſideration. But let ſuch conſider, that though the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> and many of its <hi>grand Abettors</hi> be laid flat, yet as long as ſo many <hi>Pretenders</hi> of the <hi>Family</hi> are in being, they will be always upon every opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, reviving and ſetting on foot the ſame pretences; ſo that if we ſubdue theſe by <hi>Reaſon,</hi> as well as their Perſons and Partiſans by <hi>Force,</hi> they will be the leſs able to drive on fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture deſigns, and draw Parties, either here or abroad, to the diſquiet of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:112620:4"/>
                  <p>AN ANSWER TO THE PROPOSITIONS MADE BY THE <hi>ENGLISH AMBASSADORS (as they ſtile themſelves) the</hi> 30/20 <hi>of March,</hi> In the great Aſſembly of the High and Mighty Lords, the States Generall of the United Provinces.</p>
                  <p>AS ALSO, To their <hi>Memorials</hi> of the 27/17 of <hi>April,</hi> and 20/10 of May 1651. reſpectively.</p>
                  <p>And likewiſe, To the 36. Articles of the deſired Treaty.</p>
                  <p>As it was delivered by the Honorable Sir <hi>William Macdowel</hi> Knight, Reſident for his Majeſty of Great Britain, after his return to <hi>Holland,</hi> in the ſaid <hi>Great Aſſembly, June</hi> 28/18 1651.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Prov. 24. verſe 21, 22.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>My Sonne, feare thou the Lord and the King, and meddle not with them that are given to change.</p>
                     <p>For their calamity ſhall riſe ſuddenly, and who knoweth the ruine of them?</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>HAGH,</hi> Printed by <hi>Samuel Brown,</hi> Engliſh Book-ſeller, 1651.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:112620:5"/>
                  <head>AN ANSWER TO the Propoſitions.</head>
                  <p>THe ſaid pretended <hi>Embaſſadors</hi> have offered, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all required a ſtrict <hi>Confederacy</hi> &amp; <hi>Holy League</hi> (as they term it) betwixt the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited Provinces,</hi> alledging to that end,
<list>
                        <item>I. The ancient and ſucceſſive Contracts, and mutuall Friendſhip betwixt both.</item>
                        <item>II. The advancement of Trade and Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique.</item>
                        <item>III. A Conformity in the Reformation of Religion.</item>
                        <item>IV. The like Succeſſe and Bleſſings upon both.</item>
                        <item>V. An anſwerable change in the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of both States; as likewiſe, in the reſtored Liberty of the People. <hi>Hinc inde.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which ſpecious motives, and inducements, viewed aright, and laid in a juſt ballance, will appeare (by their favours) to have no warrantable ground: For the clearing of which, the <hi>High</hi> and <hi>Mighty States</hi> are deſired to look back, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider:</p>
                  <p n="1">I: That formerly, all <hi>Contracts,</hi> have been made, betwixt the ſucceſſive <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> their lawfull <hi>Heires,</hi> and the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:112620:5"/>
                     <hi>High</hi> and <hi>Mighty State Generall,</hi> and not with <hi>England,</hi> as is alledged: Not to look further back, the <hi>Soveraignty</hi> of theſe Countries was offered to <hi>Queen Elizabeth,</hi> of happy memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, in the year 1585, which ſhe in wiſdome thought fit to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline; but, withall, aſſiſted the <hi>States,</hi> with 5000. Foot, and 1000 Horſe, as likewiſe advanced to their <hi>Lordſhips</hi> before the yeare 1596 in the ſpace of eleven years, <hi>eleven hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pounds Sterling,</hi> according to the calculation of her <hi>Majeſties</hi> Councellors, and high Treaſurer for the time.</p>
                  <p>Her Royall Succeſſors, <hi>James</hi> and <hi>Charles,</hi> of Immortall memory, in the years 1608, 1614, 1635, reſpectively, have not onely aſſiſted theſe <hi>States</hi> in their great ſtraits, in a very conſiderable way, but alſo engaged with their <hi>Lordſhips, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſivè</hi> and <hi>defenſivè,</hi> and that without the leaſt communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion had with the people of <hi>England</hi> concerning it. And, if a ratification of ſuch an alliance, ſhould be concluded with a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious Commonalty here, and that they might at pleaſure di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb the Republick, and turn matters upſide down, what an <hi>Anarchy</hi> and wofull confuſion would enſue, as now alas, we ſee too plainly followes in <hi>England?</hi> Truly, if that people had been ſo inclined, and governed, as they now are, (by thoſe who <hi>Regni cauſa</hi> have violated the rights; and to make pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe of the <hi>Lords Vineyards,</hi> have <hi>murthered him,</hi> and oppoſe with their utmoſt power and malice, the enthronement of his <hi>lawfull Heire</hi> their undoubted <hi>Soveraigne</hi>) the <hi>Low Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries</hi> ſhould not have obtained ſuch reall friendſhip and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage from them.</p>
                  <p>Beſides that, the now <hi>prevailing Party</hi> is not the hundreth part of the people in <hi>England,</hi> in compariſon of thoſe, both of the <hi>Clergie, Nobility, Gentry,</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> who cordially adhere to the <hi>Kings</hi> juſt intereſt, and paſſionatly groan to be delivered from the continued oppreſſions of thoſe cruell Taskmaſters, whoſe little finger lies heavier upon them, then all their Kings whole loins:</p>
                  <p>And an eminent Member of the late Houſe of Commons, (formerly a ſufferer) in his <hi>Memento</hi> affirms, that there is in the three Kingdomes, ten thouſand to one, who firmly and affectionatly cleave to his <hi>Majeſty.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:112620:6"/>
                  <p>In Kingdomes and Republicks (as <hi>Polititians</hi> ſpeak) it is the very ſame people now, as thoſe that lived an hundred years agoe; as likewiſe that it is the ſame ſhip, although all the planks be renewed; but if the Keel be deſtroyed, and the form of <hi>Government</hi> and <hi>Fundamentall Lawes</hi> be utterly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed, <hi>non idem populus, nec eadem navis,</hi> it is not the ſame people, nor the ſame ſhip.</p>
                  <p>Moreover, by all proofs it is ſufficiently known, that the <hi>Predeceſſors</hi> of the now prevailing Party in <hi>England,</hi> were then ſo mean and inconſiderable among the people, that they were thought utterly uncapable of having the leaſt hand in the former favours ſhewn to theſe <hi>States.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">II. <hi>Trade</hi> and <hi>Traffique</hi> (which they call (the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon intereſt of a State) are <hi>Juris Gentium,</hi> common to all Nations; conſequently, not to be carried on by <hi>Monopolies,</hi> and dammage of a third party eſpecially the eldeſt, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time the moſt conſiderable allye of this <hi>Eſtate. Amicitias</hi> (faith <hi>Polybius) it a inſtitui par eſt, ne qua vetuſtior amicitia, &amp; ſocietas violetur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is remarked by moſt of the Authors of the <hi>Netherlands Hiſtory,</hi> that their <hi>Lordſhips Predeceſſors</hi> upon a time, being more moved by the <hi>Impoſitions</hi> of the Duke of <hi>Alva,</hi> of the 10. and 100. penny <hi>reſpectivè,</hi> then for the violence offered to Religion, (and therefore compared to the <hi>Gargaſens,</hi> who proferred their ſwine before their Saviour) were the more ſeverely puniſhed by God.</p>
                  <p>And ſhall the <hi>High</hi> and <hi>Mighty States</hi> now hazard their religious and high eſteem in the ſavour of thoſe, who in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of Commerce, inlarging of their limits and uſurped power, are big with ſuch monſtrous myſteries: and of whom it was ſaid long before their troubles.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gens tacit is praegnaus arcanis ardua tentans.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Who derive their power and authority meerly from them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as formerly hath been ſaid, in the dominion of the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> over the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and of <hi>Cinna</hi> and <hi>Carbo</hi> amongſt the <hi>Romans,</hi> who in the time of <hi>Sylla</hi> made themſelves Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls without any Court election; <hi>Violenta imperia</hi> (ſaith one
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:112620:6"/>to <hi>Caeſar) ſunt magis acerba quam diuturna.</hi> The rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no Nation under the Sun is ſo ſubject to a change as <hi>England,</hi> even while they lived under their lawfull <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignes.</hi> The Earle of <hi>Warwick</hi> (called the Titular <hi>King</hi>) in eleven days, <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth in <hi>twenty, Henry</hi> the ſeventh in <hi>one day,</hi> (as a <hi>Caeſar veni, vidi, vici</hi>) brought the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſucceſſively to their obedience.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Commerce</hi> and <hi>Traffique</hi> are plauſible pretences, but often accompanied with great jealouſies, eſpecially betwixt neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Republiques; the which like Twins ſtrugling for the <hi>primogeniture,</hi> are in a continuall emulation for profit and preheminence. And therefore compared to an <hi>Alluvie,</hi> where the increaſe of one is the decreaſe of the other. Inſomuch, that grave and judicious <hi>Stateſmen</hi> have judged it would he more ſafe, and profitable to theſe States, that <hi>England</hi> continued a <hi>Monarchy,</hi> then to be tumbled into a <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by a Prognoſtication of a perſon of credit with them, living at <hi>London,</hi> given out the 16 of <hi>October</hi> laſt, alledging and applying with much confidence, againſt the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, Ierem.</hi> 51. <hi>verſ.</hi> 13.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. Concerning the pretended conformity in Religion in the third place, which, under the bleſſed and glorious Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of Kings, as a <hi>Palladium</hi> and <hi>Lamp,</hi> did out-ſhine all other Nations, is alas, now become a <hi>Pandora,</hi> out of which, <hi>tanquam ex equo Trojano,</hi> do iſſue ſo many monſtrous Sects, Hereſies and Blaſphemies, and is conſequently ſo defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, (as being utterly deſtitute of <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> and differing in moſt points of <hi>Doctrine</hi>) that it is nothing like the <hi>Religion</hi> here profeſſed, nor indeed Religion it ſelf.</p>
                  <p>A good <hi>Religion,</hi> as an upright and lively faith, iſſues forth into good <hi>Works;</hi> inſomuch that in the <hi>Primitive</hi> Church, the Chriſtians were diſcerned from the Infidels onely by their <hi>holy life,</hi> according to the proverb, <hi>Chriſtiani non ſunt Caſſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni;</hi> but alas, how many not onely <hi>Caſſii,</hi> but alſo <hi>Albii,</hi> and <hi>Nigri,</hi> are now adayes to be ſeen, witneſſe, beſides the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties intituled; <hi>Defenſio pro Carolo Rege, Vindiciae pro capite Regis Angliae, Elenchus motuum,</hi> Maſter. <hi>Prinns Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento, Theatrum Tragicum, Vox Veritatis,</hi> and others,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:112620:7"/>two Declarations alſo of the 18. of <hi>Ianuary,</hi> 1648. (long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that lamentable <hi>Cataſtrophe</hi>) by divers Preachers and learned Divines, in and about <hi>London,</hi> ſubſcribed by 126 of them, mourning over, and complaining of <hi>horrible</hi> and <hi>ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous</hi> abuſes; as in the <hi>Church,</hi> ſo in the <hi>Civill,</hi> or rather <hi>Military</hi> Government, and ſtrongly refuting their flattering of themſelves in their continued ſucceſſe, which may next be conſidered of.</p>
                  <p n="4">IV. For as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>That there be juſt men, to whom it happeneth, ſometime, according to the work of the wicked: So again, there be wicked men, to whom it happeneth according the work of the righteous.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Succeſſes often are a puniſhment, as ſometimes given for a bleſſing, where onely thoſe are to be valued, whoſe princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall aim appeares to be, the true advancement of Gods revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led will in his word; which, as it ſtrictly commandeth obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to <hi>Kings,</hi> and thoſe in authority under them, ſo it doth ſeverely puniſh ſedition and rebellion againſt them, not ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the curſe of condemnation to thoſe, who comply with, and adhere unto them. Neither hath the great <hi>Turk</hi> come far ſhort of (that undoubted bleſſing) <hi>good ſucceſſe,</hi> the now prevailing party juſtifie their cauſe, and meaſure its righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe by, though they may ſeem to diſavow him.</p>
                  <p>Finally, the reſemblance made from the manner of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered liberty of both <hi>States</hi> (to uſe the expreſſion of a great perſonage) is not more different then <hi>Mike</hi> and <hi>Ink,</hi> both in regard of the ancient condition of the people on both ſides, and the way of attaining to it.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Law Countrey men,</hi> (eſpecially the <hi>Batavi</hi>) have been reputed by all ancient Writers, for a free people, neither ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the <hi>Romans,</hi> (whom they did acknowledge onely <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villi,</hi> as <hi>Tacitus</hi> ſaith) nor to any <hi>Directors, Counts</hi> and <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors,</hi> which were conſtituted by themſelves.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Engliſh</hi> have more then a thouſand years been gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by <hi>Kings,</hi> all ſprung from the ſame Royal Stock, to whom they have ſucceſſively ſworn <hi>Obedience</hi> and <hi>Loyalty.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The King of <hi>Spain,</hi> after a war of almoſt eighty years, hath in two ſolemne Treaties (the one before the twelve yeares
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:112620:7"/>Truce, and the other in the late concluded peace) acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces</hi> to be a <hi>Free State,</hi> and that <hi>privative.</hi> Whereupon his Catholique Majeſty for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and his Succeſſors, hath diſclaimed all <hi>Pretences</hi> of <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty</hi> here.</p>
                  <p>Whereas <hi>Charls</hi> the firſt, that bleſſed Martyr (whoſe inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent blood (like that of <hi>Abels,</hi> cries loud to the higheſt Heaven for vengeance againſt thoſe who now ſit upon his Throne) not onely <hi>was,</hi> but <hi>was ever</hi> by them acknowledged for their lawfull Soveraigne, inſtead of diſclaiming his Royal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty over them, (as muſt be if the reſemblance ſtand compleat) was both deveſted of his power, deprived of his life, and his Princely Succeſſor (ſo far as in them lieth) kept back and diſenabled from the exerciſe of his undeniable power over them, whereof let them find an abſolute parallell from the <hi>Creation</hi> untill now.</p>
                  <p>In Iſrael King <hi>Ahab</hi> did tyrannize, and (as a man ſold unto ſin) above others provoked Gods wrath againſt him. In <hi>Rome</hi> there was <hi>Nero,</hi> more like a Monſter then a Man. Amongſt the Chriſtans, <hi>Christiernus</hi> in <hi>Denmark, Wencelaus</hi> in <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia,</hi> (who was likewiſe Emperour) behaved themſelves ſo wickedly, that it was ſaid of them, that they had eaſt off hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature; Not much unlike to them was <hi>Richard</hi> the third, called the Tyrant of <hi>England,</hi> yet none of all theſe was ever condemned to die by the ſentence of their ſubjects: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that it is obſerved, that the Iſraelites after they had deſerted their King <hi>Rehoboam</hi> (although an oppreſſor) never enjoyed a happy hour, but were infeſted with continual wars, both civil and forraign, til at laſt they were utterly deſtroyed, and carried captives into <hi>Babylon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Of <hi>Nero</hi> it was ſaid, <hi>primum damnati Principis exemplum,</hi> I adde <hi>poſtremum, non mactati tamen,</hi> as in this caſe. The <hi>Confederate Provinces</hi> were firſt forced in their Religion, their perſons and goods ſeized, and 100000. of them killed; The prevailing party in <hi>England,</hi> (after thoſe inſolent and high affronts done to his Majeſty, ere his conſtrained removal from his Court at <hi>White-hall,</hi>) took up <hi>Arms,</hi> gave out <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions, levied men,</hi> according to his Majeſties laſt true and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:112620:8"/>undeniable words) and ſeized upon the <hi>Regalia,</hi> before He once put himſelfe into a poſture of defence.</p>
                  <p>In the <hi>Low Countries</hi> their liberty was <hi>More Majorum,</hi> fully reſtored to them without prejudice to any man.</p>
                  <p>In <hi>England Religion</hi> and <hi>Liberty</hi> are ſhamefully trampled under foot, and the Houſe of Commons ſo diſmembred, and its priviledges violated, that the eighth part of ten, were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all parallel caſt out, as the <hi>Declaration</hi> and <hi>Protestation</hi> of the ſecluded members, <hi>Feb.</hi> 13. 1648. doth teſtifie.</p>
                  <p>The proceedings of the <hi>High</hi> and <hi>Mighty States,</hi> are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved and juſtified by all the World; on the contrary, thoſe of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> condemned and abhorred, and by themſelves confeſſed as irregular and unwarranntable; a moſt pregnant proof and <hi>probatio probata,</hi> of their wrong, as is contained in the ſaid <hi>Declaration</hi> of the Miniſters.</p>
                  <p>The which premiſes the High and Mighty <hi>States</hi> being pleaſed to take into ſerious conſideration, according to their accuſtomed wiſdome and juſtice, and calling to mind thoſe divers Treaties betwixt the <hi>Kings Royall Predeceſſors,</hi> and their <hi>Lordſhips,</hi> (in his Majeſties perſon yet firmly ſtanding.) And ſeeing likewiſe divers of their <hi>Lordſhips</hi> reſolved for a punctuall obſervation of a neutrality, ſince the yeare 1642. betwixt the late King, his <hi>Majeſties Father</hi> of bleſſed memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and his <hi>Parliament,</hi> the which by the partial confederacy with the one party, now laboured for, wil in all appearance be violated and infringed.</p>
                  <p>Therefore their Lordſhips are earneſtly intreated not to hearken to the ſaid <hi>Propoſitions,</hi> as being prejudiciall to the <hi>King</hi> my gracious Maſters intereſts, and dangerous to this State; likewiſe that the acknowledging them for a free <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick,</hi> (which poſſibly the condition of the times, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of <hi>Trade,</hi> hath occaſioned,) be not drawn into a further conſequence, much leſſe an occaſion given therby, (forge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ting <hi>Ioſephs</hi> ſufferings,) that the afflicted be yet more afflicted, their <hi>Liberty</hi> retarded, and their calamity lengthened.</p>
                  <p>His <hi>Majeſties affairs</hi> (God be praiſed) are yet in a very good and hopefull condition, farre better then ſome of his <hi>Royall Predeceſſors,</hi> who have notwithſtanding run through
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:112620:8"/>all <hi>difficulties,</hi> and became <hi>conſiderable</hi> to their <hi>friends,</hi> as <hi>formidable</hi> to their <hi>enemies.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>King Robert</hi> the <hi>Bruce,</hi> about three hundred years agoe, being likewiſe by the Rebellion of his ſubjects, and the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyaltie of the <hi>Baliol</hi> and <hi>Cumming,</hi> and their adherents, fiercely aſſailed by <hi>King Edward</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> who at once was poſſeſſed, of moſt of the Towns, and ſtrengths in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> kept a Parliament in Saint <hi>Andrews,</hi> took his Queen priſoner, killed four of his brethren, amongſt whom were thoſe <hi>duo fulmina belli,</hi> defaced or removed all the Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Regiſters of that Kingdom, was conſtrained with one or two ſervants to hide himſelf among the Hills; yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all this, in a ſhort time after, recovered his whole Kingdom was Crowned with Honor, and Glory, and forced his inſolent Enemie in confuſion to fly from <hi>Sterling</hi> to <hi>Dumbarr,</hi> and thence in a Fiſher-boat, (<hi>Xerxes</hi> like) e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcaped narrowly with his life. I ſay <hi>Sterling,</hi>
                     <q>Invictum, &amp; fatale Scotorum propugnaculum:</q> Of which 'tis ſaid:
<q>Hìc latium remorata eſt Scotia curſum.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>His Majeſties Royal Grand Father, <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, King of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Navarre,</hi> (yet of freſh memory) was in a lower condition, and had leſs power to reſiſt thoſe of the League and the powerfull King of <hi>Spain;</hi> yet at laſt became victorious, in the overthrow of his enemies, to the great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, and very conſiderable ſuccour of the <hi>Netherlands.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The diſtreſſed condition of the Predeceſſors of the <hi>High</hi> and <hi>Mighty States General,</hi> whom after ſo many changes the Almighty God hath (to the admiration of the whole World) brought into a ſafe Haven, (however <hi>Sirius</hi> a Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Writer jeſting with thoſe of <hi>Holland</hi> and their confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, did ſay, <hi>What can the Hollanders do againſt the King of Spain?</hi> as, now, ſome ſcoffingly aske, how can the <hi>Scots</hi> ſtand againſt the powerfull <hi>Engliſh?</hi>) Is an eminent, and viſible example, that it is all one, with the Lord, to help with few or with many, and that when all ſtrength, and humane hopes do fail, he will ariſe Gloriouſly, for the deliverance of the righteous, crowning them in the end, with honor and good ſucceſs.</p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:112620:9"/>
                  <p n="1">I. Shal we then look upon the preſent ſucceſſes, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of that party, as alone unchangeable, for the which ſuch ſtrange grounds are by them pretended, as are no where found, being ſo <hi>Diametrically</hi> oppoſite, according to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the ſaid Divines, in, and about <hi>London.</hi> TO
<list>
                        <item>I. Gods holy word.</item>
                        <item>II. The inſtinct of nature.</item>
                        <item>III. Natural reaſon.</item>
                        <item>IV. The Laws of all Nations.</item>
                        <item>V. The conſtitutions particularly of the Kingdome of <hi>England</hi> (who above all other people moſt obſequiouſly, and affectionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly regard and reverence their Kings) as in thoſe maxims of their Law. <hi>Rex non mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritur, Rex nulli facit injuriam,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                        <item>VI. The Judgement of all Caſuiſts.</item>
                        <item>VII. Their Oaths of Fealty, Supremacy, and Allegiance, repeated particularly at the admiſſion of every Member into the Houſe of Commons, their Proteſtation, their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, their Solemn League and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and an hundred Declarations (beſides the Pulique Faith of the Kingdom of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> ſolemnly given to the Commiſſioners of the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> upon their receiving his Majeſtie at <hi>New</hi>-Caſtle) in all which, they profeſſed to the world, that they
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:112620:9"/>would maintain and preſerve, with their lives, and Eſtates, the Kings Perſon, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, Rights, and Royal Poſterity.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">II. Or, ſhall we reſt ſatisfied in the Sophiſtry of thoſe Sectaries? who out of Chriſts anſwer to the ſubtil queſtion of the Herodians and Phariſees, (if it were lawfull to give tribute to <hi>Ceſar,</hi>) anſwered, <hi>oſtendite mihi numiſma, cujus</hi> habet imaginem? inferre, that <hi>fide implicitâ,</hi> the party now in <hi>England,</hi> is to be acknowledged, without any further en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry, or examination, ſince our Saviours anſwer ſpeaks no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for their advantage. But on the contrary, his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding Tribute to be given to <hi>Ceſar</hi> (whom the <hi>Jewes</hi> formerly acknowledged to be their King) confirmeth, and eſtabliſheth lawfull power, and conſequently condemneth ſedition and rebellion; elſe <hi>David</hi> ſhould have ſubmitted unto, and acquieſſed in the uſurped power of <hi>Abſolom,</hi> who was poſſeſſed of all the land, even unto <hi>Iordan,</hi> and carried away all <hi>Iſrael</hi> after him, and <hi>Solomon</hi> in the power of <hi>Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nijah, Iehoiada</hi> in <hi>Athalia's,</hi> and the <hi>Machabees</hi> in the power of <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes</hi> the grand enemy of the <hi>Iews,</hi> yea the Eſtates of the United Provinces ſhould have then obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the force of the Duke of <hi>Alva,</hi> who by the emblem of his Statue formerly ſet up in <hi>Antwerp,</hi> did ſignifie that he had inveſted himſelf with the abſolute power. It is well ſaid, by one of the Ancients, <hi>Omnis poteſtas eſt à Deo; ſed acquiſitio poteſtatis, furto, raepina, incendio, aut perduellione, non eſt à Deo, ſed ab hominum affectibus &amp; Satanae malitiâ.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">III. Or, may we ſuffer our ſelves to be abuſed by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples and preſidents, which the ſaid Sectaries alledg of the Kings, <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond, and <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, who, by reaſon of their incapacity, were forced to reſigne their Crowns, the one to his ſon, the other to his Competitor King <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, but neither of them to an inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:112620:10"/>ſmall remainder of an houſe of Commons, or the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Onely in a full Parliament both their reſignations were confirmed, and neither executed, but were alway afterwards honorably entertained; yea, one <hi>Roger Mortimer</hi> (which is worth the obſerving) the chief Author and actor in depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond, and Crowning his ſon <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the third in his fathers place, (according to which Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident his Majeſty, <hi>Charls</hi> the ſecond, ought by theſe to have been Crowned) was by a Parliament four years after, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with his fellow-murtherers, condemned as a Traytor, and enemy to the King and Kingdome, becauſe he killed the ſaid depoſed King in <hi>Berkley Caſtle.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Beſides, the now prevailing Party, by Solemn Proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, did publiſh and declare to all the world, that they did not intend to follow thoſe accurſed Preſidents, although they ſhould ſuffer never ſo much by the King and his Party: <hi>Exact. Collect.</hi> p. 69.</p>
                  <p n="4">IV. Should we not rather deeply apprehend, and with fear look upon thoſe exemplary puniſhments inflicted upon perjury, and Covenant-breaking in Gods holy word, as may be ſeen (to omit others, in the perſon of <hi>Saul,</hi> who toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with his poſterity, as alſo the whole Kingdome of <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,</hi> was ſo ſeverely puniſhed becauſe he deſtroyed the <hi>Gibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onits,</hi> againſt the Covenant made with <hi>Joſhua,</hi> above 200 years before, notwithſtanding they procured the ſame de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfully. As likewiſe in the Hiſtory of <hi>England,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Kingdoms, many pregnant examples to that purpoſe might be alleadged; particularly that of <hi>William Thorpe,</hi> Chief Juſtice of the Kings Bench in that Realm, who for taking a bribe of 80 pounds <hi>Sterling,</hi> was put to death, and all his goods confiſcated to the Kings uſe, in regard that in ſo doing he violated the Oath of a Judge as the words run, <hi>Quod Sacramentum Domini Regis, quod erga populum habu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it cuſtodiendum, fregit malitioſe, falſo &amp; rebelliter.</hi> Parl. 23. Edw. 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>.</p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:112620:10"/>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>An Anſwer to their Memorials..</head>
                     <p>THe Memorials I paſs over, as monſtrous, and which by inevitable conſequence, not onely tend to cut off all Treaties and alliances betwixt the Kings Majeſty and this State, and all commerce with his loyal and faithfull Subjects, but likewiſe in ſome caſes to the not ſuffering of them to dwel or reſide in theſe parts.</p>
                     <p>A demand which is againſt the band of common ſociety amongſt men, the Soveraignty of the united Provinces, and Liberty of the ſame, which have ever been a Sanctuary for honeſt men, and a receptacle of all Nations whatſoever: In a word ſuch, <hi>quale victor victo dare, non ſocius ſocium rogare ſolet.</hi> The cruelty of <hi>Tiberius, Nero, Domitian,</hi> and others hath for the moſt part been confined within the walls of <hi>Rome,</hi> or the borders of <hi>Italy,</hi> without perſecuting their oppoſers, in a ſtrange land as an, <hi>omnibus umbra locis adero.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Concerning the thirty ſix Articles of the Treaty.</head>
                     <p>The thirty ſix Articles evidently bend,
<list>
                           <item>I. TO hinder his Majeſties Juſt Right, and Reſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to his hereditary Crown, and Kingdom of <hi>England.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>II. To involve the High and Mighty States Generall in a Labyrinth and great inconveniencies, who at preſent have no enemy.</item>
                           <item>III. To encourage and ſtrengthen the Kings irreconcila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble enemies, and Rebels, as the 4, 5, 6, and 31 Articles doe import.</item>
                           <item>IV. Againſt the forementioned reſolutions of the High and Mighty States, in the year 1642, concerning the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping a Neutrality betwixt his Majeſties Father of bleſſed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:112620:11"/>memory, and his Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> namely thoſe of the 1 of <hi>November,</hi> and 30 of <hi>December</hi> 1642 and the 6 of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember</hi> 1648.</item>
                           <item>V. Againſt a Declaration and Proteſtation of the Noble and Mighty States of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Frieſland,</hi> dated the 6 of <hi>November</hi> 1649 to the ſame purpoſe.</item>
                           <item>VI. Againſt all former Treaties, and Alliances betwixt his Majeſties Royall Predeceſſors and this State.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>As amongſt others, that of the 14 of <hi>February</hi> 1593 (like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe conſiſting of 36 Articles) betwixt King <hi>Henry</hi> the 7 of <hi>England,</hi> his Heirs and Succeſſors, made in his name, and by his Authority (as the words of the ſaid Treaty do bear) and <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> Arch Duke of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and Duke of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> which binde and obliege to this very day, divers of the United Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, and the chief Members and Towns thereof, to aſſiſt the ſaid King <hi>Henry</hi> the 7 and his Heirs (which unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionably pleadeth for my Maſter, <hi>Charls</hi> the ſecond, he being the ſixth from him in deſcent <hi>in linea recta</hi>) and to afford them all favour and friendly aſſiſtance, as well by Sea as by Land, and prohibiteth any Treaty and Alliance to be made with the Rebels, and the Enemies of one another.</p>
                     <p>Whoſe undoubted right, according to Gods ſacred word, the Lawes, and the Fundamentall Conſtitutions of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>England</hi> as, (<hi>Rex non moritur,</hi> &amp;c.) is firmly radica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in his Majeſties Perſon, however he by violence be kept from it.</p>
                     <q>
                        <hi>Non unquam perdidit ordo Mutato ſua Jura loco.</hi>
                     </q>
                     <p>In ſo much that the ancient <hi>Romans</hi> by the light of nature did refuſe to enter into any Alliance with <hi>Nabis</hi> the <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper</hi> of <hi>Lacedaemon,</hi> but continued the ſame with the Juſt and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full King <hi>Pelopides. Amicitia &amp; ſocietas nobis nulla tecum eſt</hi> ſaith <hi>Tit: Quintius</hi> in the behalf of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, <hi>apud Livium</hi> lib. 34.) <hi>Sed cum Pelopide Rege Lacedaemoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum justo &amp; ligitimo facta eſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Finally againſt the renewed Treaty in the year 1550. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember</hi> 15. made at <hi>Bins</hi> in <hi>Henegow</hi> (called the <hi>Perpetuall
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:112620:11"/>Treaty</hi>) betwixt the tutors of <hi>Mary</hi> Q of <hi>Scotland,</hi> in her mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nority, and Queen <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Hungary,</hi> Regent for <hi>Charls</hi> the fifth in the <hi>Low-Countreys,</hi> renewed again <hi>in ſolenni for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> (word by word) at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> 1594. betwixt King <hi>James</hi> the ſixth and the <hi>High</hi> and <hi>Mighty States,</hi> after the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of the Late Prince <hi>Henry,</hi> his Majeſties ſon, celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at <hi>Sterling.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In the which it is promiſed and agreed upon, <hi>inviola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly</hi> to <hi>maintain</hi> and <hi>preſerve</hi> mutuall friendſhip one with another, for <hi>all ages</hi> to <hi>come,</hi> and as farre as in them lay, to <hi>prevent,</hi> and <hi>hinder</hi> any <hi>dammage</hi> that may befall either of them, that they ſhall Trafique in ſafety and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, and likewiſe, that they ſhall aſſiſt each other with Ships, and all ſort of <hi>Ammunition,</hi> as may be ſeen at length in the Treaty it ſelf, inſerted by <hi>Peter Borr</hi> in his 30 book.</p>
                     <p>But how oppoſite this is to their 4, 5, and 31 Articles pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to your Lordſhips, appeareth clearly out of the words there contained, where they not onely deny to the King and his Subjects, <hi>privativè,</hi> all favour, friendſhip, and proviſion of War, but likewiſe endeavour to obliege your Lordſhips, <hi>De facto,</hi> to infeſt and make war upon them, as having now no other Enemies (as they themſelves give out) but <hi>Scotland.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But expecting better things of the <hi>High</hi> and <hi>Mighty States,</hi> and a Religious obſervation of all Treaties, Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, Proteſtations, and Declarations; Your Lordſhips are intreated not to give ear to the ſaid Propoſitions, and Memorials, as alſo that the ſaid 36 Articles periſhing in their birth, may not be taken into any further Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
                     <p>The Lord will reward every one according to his works, and I wiſh that he may ever bleſs the <hi>High</hi> and <hi>Mighty States</hi> with his Fatherly Protection, and keep them from contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting any League and Alliance, which may be attended with Diſhonor and Dammage unto them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:112620:12"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:112620:12"/>
                  <p>ANIMADVERSIONS UPON A CERTAIN SCOTTISH ANSWER, SET FORTH AGAINST The Propoſitions &amp; Memorandums OF THE Engliſh Ambaſſadors, &amp;c. SERVING For a right Information of the plainer Sort.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>ROM. 13.1.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Let every Soul be ſubject to the Higher Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: For there is no Power but of GOD, and the powers which are, are ordained of GOD.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>PROV. 24.21.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Fear the King, <hi>[that is to ſay]</hi> All Magiſtrates.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>Written and printed firſt in <hi>Dutch</hi> by a Gentleman of <hi>Holland,</hi> and now tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>London,</hi> Re-printed 1651.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:112620:13"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Animadverſions</hi> Upon a certain <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Anſwer, put forth againſt the <hi>Propoſitions</hi> and <hi>Memorandums</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh Ambaſſadors, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Anſwerer</hi> hath this expreſſion in the Title of his Anſwer, <hi>[By the Engliſh Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors, as they ſtile themſelves]</hi> juſt as if no body elſe did acknowledge them for ſuch. Such an untruth appearing preſently in the Front, makes every one gueſſe the Houſe is alike furniſhed within. Not they themſelves, but the K of <hi>Spain,</hi> the K. of <hi>Portugall,</hi> the State of <hi>Venice,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Florence,</hi> the Republick of <hi>Genua,</hi> doe thus ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge them. And the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> himſelfe knowes very well, that the ſupream power of this Place hath done the ſame.</p>
                  <p>From the Text, <hi>Feare God and the King,</hi> the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> would fain inferre, that they ought both to be feared in one and the ſame degree, taxing thereby this very State as much as the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> We muſt fear God more then men. The King is a man: the <hi>Scots</hi> themſelves did underſtand it ſo, when as in the late troubles they perſecuted their King by warre, and at laſt delivered him up unto the <hi>Engliſh</hi> for money; as the ſaid King himſelf profeſſeth in the 23 Chapter of his printed Book of <hi>Meditations.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the beginning of the Diſcourſe the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> alledges, That the ancient Contracts and Friendſhips were not made between <hi>England</hi> and this State, but between the Kings of <hi>England</hi> and this State. And wherefore ſaith he not, between the Kings of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> reſpectively? but that he is convinced that State, that is to ſay, the Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatives of the Countries, and the People, are<note n="*" place="margin">A Dutch phraſe.</note> the <hi>Bride for whom is danced,</hi> The King or Prince is for the peoples ſake, not the people for the Kings ſake.</p>
                  <p>The King of <hi>Denmark</hi> ſaid likewiſe in the beginning: He
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:112620:13"/>and his Predeceſſors had contracted with the Duke of <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundie,</hi> with the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> not with the <hi>States;</hi> he knew no <hi>States,</hi> and denied any treaty with them. But his Majeſty hath been better informed ſince, having of his own accord often deſired a Treaty with theſe States, as other Kings and Potentates have done, who thereby doe and muſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that a <hi>King</hi> or <hi>Prince</hi> doth and ought to do all in dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, treating, or tranſacting, <hi>propopulo, pro ſalute populi:</hi> For the people, for the weale of the people (which is the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Law) not for himſelfe. That the name of the King or Prince is uſed therein, no otherwiſe but <hi>Nomine procuratorio, vel tutorio,</hi> as a Truſtee, or Guardian. So their Lordſhips the Sta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es underſtood it alſo, when on <hi>May</hi> 2. laſt paſt, they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented unto the <hi>Engliſh Embaſſadors,</hi> the ancient Treaty of 1495. made in the Names of the King of <hi>England,</hi> and the Archduke of <hi>Auſtria.</hi> King <hi>James</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi> implied as much when he ſought in <hi>Anno</hi> 1594. to renew the old Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie (with the States Generall) formerly made in the name of Queen <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> 1541, which agreeth in every re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect with the practice of all other Princes.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Anſwerer</hi> ſaith, That the States in <hi>Anno</hi> 1584, did offer the Soveraignty of theſe Countries to Q. <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> To what purpoſe he utters this, I cannot imagine; For, it will not follow thence, that this State cannot be allowed to treat with the State of <hi>England,</hi> though there be no King; ſince the ſaid Queen, and the Kings after her treated with us, even af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we had caſt off our King, as the <hi>Engliſh</hi> have now done theirs:</p>
                  <p>If this State made offer of the Soveraignty to Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> doubtles it was on certain conditions; which if ſhe or her Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors had not kept, we ſhould not have ſcrupled to have reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered the ſame into our hands again, even as the <hi>Engliſh</hi> have don. Among the <hi>Barbarians</hi> and Savages it is confeſt indeed, that their Kings wil be bound to no Laws, (though oft-times they fare accordingly: For, how many have there been even in our times, of <hi>Turkiſh</hi> &amp; other Heathen Emperours &amp; Kings made away?) But among <hi>Chriſtians</hi> no King or Prince was ever heard of, but he muſt ſwear to maintain the Laws. If any
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:112620:14"/>Prince prove perjured and break them, ſo ſoon as the breach is made, the people are freed from their obedience.</p>
                  <p>The ſupply both of men and money which the <hi>Queen</hi> ſent for our reliefe, came from the people themſelves, and out of the peoples purſe; the people did conſent unto it, and grant it. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntrue therefore</hi> it is, which the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> affirmes, that the ſaid ſuccour and aſſiſtance was ſent without the co-opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or conſent of the people of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If the people of <hi>England</hi> had any Monarch at this inſtant, to whom they had given up the power of Treating, then our addreſſes of Treaty ſhould be made to him; but there being no ſuch thing, and we not able to ſubſiſt without the friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of <hi>England,</hi> therefore we muſt treat with <hi>England</hi> as it is now governed.</p>
                  <p>And truly the late Summers proceedings and attempt in this Countrey, (when our own Freedom ran greateſt hazard) may well awake us to circumſpection, and cauſe us to rejoyce that <hi>England</hi> is no Monarchy now, but a Free State, of the ſame conſtitution with ours, and to wiſh that thus it may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue; For, all the dependants and kindred of the young Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> maintain ſtill, we ought, muſt, &amp; are bound both by the merits of the Houſe of <hi>Naſſau,</hi> and for our own ſubſiſtence ſake, to take the young <hi>Prince</hi> again for our Head, Generall and Governor: And were the King of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> maſter of <hi>England,</hi> he would maintain it as ſtrongly as any, and ſeek to force the child upon us.</p>
                  <p>As for the favours and aſſiſtances that King <hi>James</hi> and <hi>Charles</hi> afforded us, they doe not merit naming; we had more hurt then good by them. And King <hi>Charles</hi> never kept touch with us, as is well known. If in thoſe times the people or Parliament had been in Government, as now they are, they would have better managed the Revenews of <hi>England</hi> (which Kings waſte, or play away) to procure our effectuall liberty, ſuch as now both <hi>England</hi> and we enjoy, but not after the method that <hi>Leiceſter intended.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Anſwerer</hi> ſaith, that the prevailing party make not up the hundreth part of the people of <hi>England.</hi> Why truly then the <hi>Ninety-nine Royaliſts</hi> that ſuffer one <hi>Parliamenteer</hi> to do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineer
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:112620:14"/>it over them, muſt be very notable Cowards.</p>
                  <p>I am ſure there were ſeven or eight <hi>Royaliſts</hi> at the <hi>hague</hi> made a ſhift to diſpatch one <hi>Doriſlaus,</hi> and at <hi>Madrid</hi> onely five or ſix did murther <hi>Aſcham;</hi> but an hundred to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come and kept under by one, how is it poſſible? This Tale hath for theſe many years been pin'd to our ſleeves; yet ſtill the <hi>Parliamenteers</hi> get the better, and keep the better.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Englands</hi> greateſt Power, the flower of the Parliaments Forces, is now in <hi>Scotland;</hi> I marvell the <hi>ninety-nine</hi> to one are ſo tame and quiet ſtill in <hi>England;</hi> as nowhere to ſhew themſelves.</p>
                  <p>The compariſon of <hi>England</hi> with a ſhip, doth hold as good a proportion as the <hi>ninety-nine</hi> to one. The <hi>Engliſh</hi> people and Nation is and abides the ſame it was; the <hi>individuals</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay, the <hi>ſpecies</hi> remains. A <hi>Ship</hi> and a <hi>People</hi> fit as well as a <hi>Cat</hi> and a <hi>Duck;</hi> but I conceive the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> means the Trees whereof the ſhip is built: for they do propagate and multiply according to their kind, like men, and that is more ſutable to the opinion of ſome ſoothing <hi>Court-Paraſites,</hi> ſuch as our <hi>Anſwerer</hi> proves himſelfe, that ſubjects are no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then trees: others compare them to beaſts, as if a Prince were ſo much better then the ſubjects, as another man is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then a beaſt: that is to ſay, The beaſts are beaſts to men, but the ſubjects are their Princes beaſts; A beaſtly opinion.</p>
                  <p>The entercourſes of Commerce, ſaith the <hi>Anſwerer,</hi> are common to all Nations; Why then the King of <hi>Scotland</hi> doth very ill in ſtopping and moleſting the free and common com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce of all Nations from the <hi>Sillies, Ierſie, Ireland, Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerk,</hi> &amp;c. to ſo great prejudice of the Seamen, that the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage in this kinde can no longer be endured. The <hi>Engliſh</hi> have the ſame aim with us, for clearing of the ſea. I cannot tell what he means by his <hi>Gargazens Trade. Navigation</hi> is the life of this State: <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Trade</hi> doe not deſtroy one another, as it ſeems he would inferre; and how doth he talk of Religion? He himſelfe is profeſſedly againſt the Epiſcopall way (which all the <hi>Royaliſts</hi> and the <hi>Princeſſe Royall,</hi> and the <hi>Queen</hi> of <hi>Bohemia</hi> are ſtill addicted to) and holds with the <hi>Presbyterians;</hi> with whom our own people (for matter of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:112620:15"/>
                     <hi>Excommunication</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline</hi>) do not agree. He ſaith farther, <hi>Violent Governments are not laſting:</hi> By that rule, no <hi>Monarchicall</hi> Government ſhould be laſting; for their Sword onely doth ſupport them. He ſaith <hi>England</hi> is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to great alterations, yea, more than any Countrey under the Sun. He means under Kingly Government: But by and by he ſowes jealouſies, by ſaying, that <hi>England</hi> continuing a Commonwealth, it is like to increaſe mightily in Trade and Navigation, and that the increaſe of Trade in <hi>England,</hi> will make ours to decay in <hi>Holland.</hi> Theſe aſſertions do mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thwart one another. Firſt, he ſays; There is 100 <hi>Roya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts</hi> to one Parliamentier; then, <hi>England</hi> is extreamly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to changes and alterations; within the ſpace of 11 or 20 days, it hath been loſt and won; and then preſently after he ſaith, <hi>England</hi> continuing a Republique, will make our Trade decay. <hi>Ergò</hi> his minde and fear prompts him, that the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Republique may well endure ſomewhat more then 11 or 20 days. Theſe Paſſages of his contradicting each other, are an Argument of a ſhort memory, or that he goes about to abuſe us with <hi>flim flam</hi> tales. For, how doth it appear that our Trade ſhall be ſpoiled by the <hi>Engliſh?</hi> They ſend and offer us reall aſſiſtance and protection againſt the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold depredations we ſuffer by others.</p>
                  <p>If both theſe Republicks were well united, yet the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Monarchies round about them, will finde work e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for both to maintain their Negotiations jointly: How much leſs then is <hi>England</hi> alone like to get all the Trade to themſelves? The Engliſh may be ſtrugling a good while yet, before a ſecure ſetling; they will not want enemies at home and abroad, to make attempts upon them; as the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerer</hi> himſelf confeſſeth.</p>
                  <p>The Prognoſtick of <hi>October</hi> 16 which he ſpeaks of, is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuation of the ſame nature with thoſe Victories, ſucceſſes, and advantages which he daily forged, and printed here laſt Summer, which by the Blow at <hi>Dunbar</hi> evaporated all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately. Thoſe that tell us of <hi>Almanacks</hi> and <hi>Prognoſticks,</hi> ſhew they have but few and ſlender Reaſons left them to produce. I could reply to him out of <hi>Spinrock</hi>'s Goſpell.</p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:112620:15"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Religion,</hi> ſaith he, was wont to ſhine forth under the <hi>Kingly Government.</hi> How comes this Anſwerer to praiſe the Kings Religion, when as himſelf as well as the reſt of his <hi>Scots</hi> Countreymen, have not onely made the firſt inſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt the Kings Religion; but entred into a Covenant and raiſed war, and at laſt ſold the King for money (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Kings own publiſhed profeſſion; Principally againſt the Kings Religion, or againſt the innovation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of at leaſt. And what the King ſaid further of the <hi>Scots</hi> Religion, and conſequently of the <hi>Anſwerers</hi> Religion, you may read at large in the 14 and 16 Chapters of his printed Book. It is well known what harſh and bitter Sermons and Books were made but lately at <hi>Breda</hi> and the <hi>Hague,</hi> againſt the <hi>Reformed Religon,</hi> whom they ſtill hatefully termed <hi>Calviniſts.</hi> Are there in <hi>England</hi> divers Sects? there are here alſo not a few, God mend it; and even as the Governors here would gladly ſee it otherwiſe, ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe thoſe in <hi>England;</hi> in the mean time, we are aſſured, that in <hi>England</hi> divers books are forbidden, and were burnt by the <hi>Hangman,</hi> which here paſſe up and downe yet every where.</p>
                  <p>The Ambaſſadors have in the Name and behalf of the whole Engliſh Government, declared the Conformity of their Religion with ours. They tolerate ſome others; and ſo do we; onely we allow more and greater toleration then they: Neither we nor they approve of a <hi>Spaniſh Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They do not allow the Church an abſolute power of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication; no more do we; and the Scottiſh Kirk al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo was fain to remit it now themſelves. So that the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians rage and roaring againſt Sects and Sectaries is groundleſs; for between themſelves and the Independents (ſo named) there is not difference in the main of Religion, or profeſſion, beſides Diſcipline; but it ſhould ſeem the Presbyterian <hi>Boutefeus,</hi> aim at a <hi>Papall Power,</hi> to admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the <hi>Jus Clavium</hi> at pleaſure, as the <hi>Scots</hi> have: But their young King hath already taught them another Leſſon; diſapproving thereby alſo the Engliſh Presbyterians, It were
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:112620:16"/>much to be wiſhed indeed, that all men were of one minde; that there were but one Religion: Our <hi>Anſwerer</hi> I believe knows as little how to adviſe or compaſs it, as others. Nay, he himſelf refuſing to go to the ſame Church where the King went, during his abode here, and the Queen of <hi>Bohemia</hi> and the Princeſs Royal, and all the Royaliſts, doth thereby ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently evidence, that there are ſects and diviſions, as well between his party and the Kings, as there is between the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> and the <hi>Presbyterians.</hi> That which he mentioneth of the good life of his Royal Chriſtians, I profeſs, I underſtand not: If by a good life he means, a merry, joviall life, <hi>(dum vixit, vixit bene)</hi> I yeild, that at Court they live more merrie and frollick then elſewhere; and thence it is, that at <hi>London</hi> they have put down all the Play-Houſes, and ſuch like pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and practiſes of profane and ſcandalous recreation. That otherwiſe the life and fruitfull Converſation of the Royaliſts ſhould be more holy and exemplary, then that of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Independents, as they call them, I never heard of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Were they not the Kings evil Councellors, his flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, and ſeducers (whom I return to the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> for his <hi>Albii, Caſſii, Nigri</hi>) that made as well the Presbyterians, as the reſt, complaine ſo much againſt him from time to time?</p>
                  <p>And I pray, were not the Presbyterians the firſt and the onely men, that took the King to task? The <hi>Anſwerer</hi> himſelf was one of them, and of thoſe Covenanters, that ſupplanted the King, for his maintaining the <hi>Epiſcopal Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erarchie:</hi> And when the Presbyterians afterwards went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to introduce the <hi>Presbyterian Hierarchie</hi> (changing onely the Name, and maintaining the Subſtance) then ſaid the others whom he calls <hi>Independents,</hi> Soft my Maſters; we have freed our ſelves from the Biſhops Yoke; ſhall we put our necks under the <hi>Presbyterians?</hi> The <hi>Anſwerer</hi> alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſome other books which make for him. How many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther blew books might eaſily be produced againſt the ſame, and to his prejudice?</p>
                  <p>The King himſelf complains in his book <hi>ch.</hi> 15. and 21. how much hurt theſe books did him; ſo that I know not why the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> ſo highly eſteems theſe blew books, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:112620:16"/>that publickly in print too now, as well as in the <hi>Generall Aſſembly;</hi> odiouſly checking the Soveraign Government here, for having begun to treat with the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly ſpreading the ſame abroad among the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons; as though the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> were regardleſs of their Office; and as if he intended to incenſe and raiſe the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> againſt the <hi>Governors<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> contemning the publick O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances in this behalf. As for the <hi>Succeſſes;</hi> the <hi>Anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> knows well enough that ſeveral other Kings, Republicks, Princes and Potentates had beforehand acknowledged the Republick of <hi>England</hi> and honored the ſame with their Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſies, and Credentials: And <hi>England</hi> alſo ſent firſt unto this State, before this State ſent to <hi>England.</hi> We have not looked upon the ſucceſſes, but upon the Example of others.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Anſwerer ſaith,</hi> that the <hi>Engliſh th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mſelves</hi> do diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vow the great <hi>Turk:</hi> Again, the <hi>Gentleman</hi> throwes it beyond my reach, or he knows not what he avers himſelf. I never heard of any ſuch Diſavowing; but this I know well on the contrary, that all <hi>Chriſtian Potentates,</hi> acknowledge the <hi>Turk</hi> for what He is, and accordingly honor him with their <hi>Ambaſſies:</hi> The <hi>Anſwerer's</hi> King himſelf, ſcrupled not to ſend to the <hi>Turk;</hi> no more doth the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Republick. Men, Laws, Governments, muſt every where be taken and uſed as they are. As long as the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> and his King are forced to let the Government remain as it is, ſo they muſt give us leave to do the ſame.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Anſwerer</hi> ſaith, that there is as much difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government and Liberty, and that of ours, as there is between <hi>Milk</hi> and Ink, according to the ſaying of one <hi>Salmaſius,</hi> calling him a great Perſonage. Sure the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> knows well that <hi>Salmaſius</hi> his Book, where he had this <hi>crotchet,</hi> is publickly declared a Libell and ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous here. Do great Perſonages uſe to write Libells?</p>
                  <p>Furthermore, He ſaith, That the <hi>Batavians</hi> or <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> have been a Free Nation from all ages, and under the ſubjection of none. Certainly he is a dreaming; or elſe he hath the art to make white black, and black white, at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: or, <hi>Milk</hi> and Ink is all one to him. What, hath not
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:112620:17"/>
                     <hi>Holland</hi> been under Earls above eight hundred years? And laſtly, under the Houſe of <hi>Burgundy, Auſtria,</hi> and <hi>Spain?</hi> Indeed the <hi>Earls</hi> were tied to <hi>Laws,</hi> and ſo were the Kings of <hi>England;</hi> if he ſay, an <hi>Earl</hi> is no <hi>King;</hi> I anſwer, <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is divided in more then fifty Counties, or Earldomes; ſo <hi>France</hi> is divided into many principalities and Counties. He that gets the command over them, ſoon gets a Title, <hi>King, Prince, Earl,</hi> or <hi>Lord;</hi> it comes all to one, if they have no Superiours. But all of them are bound to their Oaths, and the Laws. Neither in <hi>France,</hi> nor in <hi>Spain,</hi> nor anywhere elſe, are Kings allowed an unlimited power. The Examples in <hi>France</hi> are too freſh to rehearſe them.</p>
                  <p>The Kings of <hi>Spain</hi> have been Earls of <hi>Holland,</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged no ſuperiors; now being freed from <hi>Spain,</hi> there is none appearing that pretend any right to <hi>Holland.</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe he was bound to the laws by an oath.</p>
                  <p>So that King of <hi>England</hi> was Earle of <hi>Eſſexſhire, Suſſex, Yorkshire,</hi> and of all the reſt, compendiouſly called King of <hi>England, Scotland, Ireland,</hi> but bound to the Lawes.</p>
                  <p>They of <hi>Holland</hi> perceiving their King had infringed the Laws, thereupon they oppoſed him, and fought themſelves free; <hi>Bene &amp; feliciter</hi> (ſaith the King of <hi>Spains</hi> Embaſſador Count <hi>Pigneranda) pro libertate pugnaſtis; ea vobis debetur.</hi> The <hi>Engliſh</hi> in like manner perceived their King had treſpaſſed againſt the laws, and falſified his oath, whereupon they op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed him til they fought themſelves into the ſame condition of <hi>Freedom.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I could ſay ſomewhat more here: That the King of <hi>England</hi> out-did <hi>Spain.</hi> He of <hi>Spain</hi> had ſworn to the <hi>Roman</hi> Religion, and conceived himſelf bound to protect it according to his <hi>Oath:</hi> but the King of <hi>England</hi> being ſworn to the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion, is charged to have acted againſt it, innovated it, and had he gotten the maſtery, would have changed it.</p>
                  <p>That this Aſſertion (owned as well by the <hi>Scots</hi> as the <hi>Engliſh</hi>) is moſt true, appeares by the <hi>Covenant,</hi> firſt made by the <hi>Scots,</hi> and afterwards embraced alſo by the <hi>Engliſh:</hi> Look upon <hi>Chapt.</hi> 14. of the <hi>Kings Book,</hi> ſee what he ſaith there himſelfe of the <hi>Covenant:</hi> Again, the <hi>Covenant</hi> very expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:112620:17"/>ſhewed, that the King had an intent to alter Religion and Laws. The <hi>Anſwerer</hi> himſelfe was a <hi>Covenanter</hi> and <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamenteer,</hi> and blew as fiercely and zealouſly as any againſt the Kings deſigne of Innovation, as they termed it. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond and third Article of the <hi>Covenant</hi> ſpeaks very plain. And there have been a thouſand books written both by the <hi>Scots</hi> &amp; <hi>Engliſh Presbyterians</hi> on that ſubject. Nay, the <hi>Scots</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have even ſince the late Kings death, excommunicated all that had and did adhere to the King (calling them <hi>Enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi>) and declared them <hi>Given over to the Devill.</hi> And for this cauſe they put poore <hi>Montroſſe</hi> to death, and refuſed him <hi>Abſolution.</hi> And what afterwards the King himſelf, and <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milton, Middleton, Lauderdale,</hi> &amp; others of this party, have ſuffered, is notorious to all the world. Alſo, how this King was fain to do penance, and to confeſs the bloud guiltineſs of his Father's Houſe. How ever, all the difference betwixt the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> was only this; that He of <hi>England</hi> did more, and He of <hi>Spain,</hi> leſs againſt the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion that each of them was ſworn to.</p>
                  <p>It is well known, that the <hi>Scots</hi> were the firſt, that made a <hi>Covenant,</hi> and thereupon took up arms, even as the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility heretofore in the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> made a League or U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and took up arms to defend it. The <hi>Scots</hi> having clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their own Land of all the <hi>Royall</hi> deſigns and adherents, were not content therewith, but proceeded to aſſiſt the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh,</hi> who were as eager to be rid of the ſame incumbrances. Which being effected, and the King brought to this paſs, that he ſaw no remedy left him, then he betook himſelf to the <hi>Scots</hi> at laſt, his own Country men, as confiding more in them. Why did not the <hi>Scots</hi> then take him home along with them? They ſaid, it was not expedient; the <hi>King</hi> might eaſily put <hi>Scotland</hi> into new broils, as the <hi>Engliſh</hi> found afterwards among themſelves; for then broke firſt out thoſe differences betwixt <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>Independents;</hi> the former would have a new <hi>Hierarchy</hi> introduced, like that of the <hi>Scots;</hi> the later would have the <hi>Reformed Religion</hi> maintained, as it now ſtands among them, only they would bear with <hi>tender conſciences,</hi> and ſome others, as wee doe likewiſe here.</p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:112620:18"/>
                  <p>The King of <hi>Spain</hi> hath given up his Right, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged this a <hi>Free State:</hi> had the King of <hi>England</hi> done the like, or would this King content himſelf yet with the <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh</hi> Crown, as his Fore-fathers did, the war would ſoon be at an end. And herein <hi>Philip</hi> ſhewed himſelf more reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable and righteous, then <hi>Charls,</hi> whom nevertheleſs hee ſtyles, that <hi>Bleſſed Martyr,</hi> ſo highly wronged and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, not remembring, at leaſt concealing, that they were the <hi>Scots,</hi> who began this violent dealing with him. But none of this concerns us, not can we help it. If the <hi>Scots</hi> vvill begin troubles and war, and the Neighbour Kings and Potentates, will wink at it, vvhat is that to us?</p>
                  <p>What is farther ſaid by the <hi>Anſwerer,</hi> about the Kings death, concerns not us of <hi>Holland</hi> at all. If a King wageth war with his ſubjects, he muſt needs reſolve to run the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard. Kings and Princes are fleſh and bloud, and mortal as well as others. As much might have been done in a Charge by the Sword of a <hi>private ſoldier,</hi> as was afterwards by the hand of the <hi>Executioner.</hi> The Quality or Majeſty of a King or Prince, is of no conſideration to the ſteel or lead of the meaneſt ſoldier, <hi>&amp; noſtro ſequitur de vulnere ſanguis. Majeſtate nihil contemtius, nec infirmius, ſi ſint qui contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. A living Dog is better then a dead Lion.</hi> A Peſant, owner of ſome Land, is better then a King, vvithout Land. He that vvill not ſubmit himſelf to the Diſcretion of a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour,</hi> ſhould not runne the hazard of being conquered. The <hi>Conquering party</hi> ſaw no other <hi>Expedient,</hi> no farther truſt given; even during the Kings reſtraint, there was fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction upon faction, diviſion upon diviſion, inſurrection upon inſurrection raiſed. The meaneſt creature, the pooreſt worm ſeeks for ſelf-preſervation. How much more a Man? If there had been any means left under Heaven, whereby a firm confidence could have been recovered, it is very proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the <hi>Prevailing party</hi> would have yeilded to it. But to put all their Fortunes, Reputation, Freedom, Life, and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, upon a new hazard again, no Reaſon could adviſe them.</p>
                  <p>Now, as to the matter of depoſing, and deſtroying of Kings, it is ſo common, both in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:112620:18"/>I admire, why the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> makes it ſo ſtrange and prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious. But all theſe things are ſo largely ſet forth in print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Boooks and Pamphlets, that the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> hath little rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to make a wonder of it. <hi>Omnia jam vulgata.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To make an alliance with <hi>England</hi> were unneceſſary if our Commerce and Liberties were not in danger. We are bound to look to their preſervation. The Depredations are unſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable! We do not afflict the afflicted; but thoſe whom he calls the afflicted, afflict us.</p>
                  <p>As for the affliction of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> we know not what it means, unleſs he make <hi>Joſeph</hi> a <hi>Cavalier;</hi> and under that notion the <hi>Scots</hi> themſelves were the firſt that perſecuted him. And that party in <hi>Scotland</hi> which the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> himſelf doth eſteem the honeſter, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>kirk party,</hi> they abhor the <hi>Royaliſts,</hi> calling them <hi>Malignants.</hi> The <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ambaſſadors have declared here in their firſt Propoſition, they came not out of neceſſity, but to ſhew, they were willing to chooſe this State for their beſt friends. They have not deſired to ingage us againſt the <hi>Scots.</hi> But it is well known both to them and us, what practices and mighty indeavours, the <hi>Royal party</hi> hath uſed theſe many years to ingage this State againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, now the Common-wealth of <hi>England.</hi> What par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial proceedings were there a foot? All that came from the <hi>King,</hi> had audience at pleaſure; the <hi>Parliament</hi> none. The Stateſ-men of war, were (though moſtly beſides the States knowledge) imployed in the ſervice of the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Party,</hi> as if they had been his own. What would have been the iſſue think you, if they had ingaged us to make war againſt the Parliament, but to ſacrifice our Power, our Treaſure, our Freedome, for the inſlaving both the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and our Selves? Is it forgotten already, what paſt here among us laſt Summer? Had <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> and the Bank of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> been but ſurpriſed once, nay, had but <hi>one man</hi> continued alive, we ſhould have been in a caſe ſad and bad enough.</p>
                  <p>After that this danger was over, and we had called the <hi>Grand Aſſembly</hi> together, for the ſettlement of our Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, they acknowledged the Common-wealth of <hi>England,</hi>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:112620:19"/>and reſolved to ſend an Ambaſſador to them; the Parliament ſhewed themſelves ſo honourable and civil, that they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented us, concurring with our own deſires, of ſettling both theſe <hi>Republicks,</hi> in a poſture againſt all that ſhould at any time attempt ought againſt them. They conſidered who was their preſent Enemy, and how near the King of <hi>Scots</hi> was allied to him, that by his late practiſes diſcloſed ſo much of his Deſigns againſt <hi>Holland, Amſterdam,</hi> and the whole State. Alſo what ſpecial correſpondence there paſt between theſe two, to reduce both <hi>Republicks</hi> to a plenary Subjection. Afterwards when the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had gotten the ſtart of their Adverſary, by the great Victory at <hi>Dunbar:</hi> Then it is to be obſerved, that they came out of a cordially zeal and affection to deliver us likewiſe, and to further the ſettlement of our State, and by an union with them, render us ſecure at home, and feared abroad. How, and by whom the effect thereof hath been protracted hitherto, is well known; namely, by thoſe who ſtill are Preaching to us, that we ſhould ſubmit our ſelves under the young Prince of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range;</hi> that is to ſay, under the ſiſter of the King of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> the Guardianeſs of him, whom they would fain force upon us for our Head and Guardian.</p>
                  <p>The following both Scripture and prophane Allegations and Hiſtories regiſtred by the <hi>Anſwerer,</hi> are to no purpoſe, being a thouſand times refuted. Gods holy Word, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct of Nature, right reaſon, the Laws, the Judgements of the Caſuiſts, the Oaths, Covenants, and all theſe are things the Parliament alledge for themſelves, with more reaſon and advantage, then the <hi>Royaliſts.</hi> Thoſe ſayings, <hi>Rex non mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritur, &amp; Rex nulli facit injuriam,</hi> are known to be rank flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, and neither in <hi>England,</hi> nor in any other Kingdome allowed of. I wonder how this man durſt avert ſuch things in the face of this <hi>Republick.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As alſo, that he durſt call that a <hi>Sophiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e,</hi> which the States of <hi>Holland</hi> had made uſe of, to induce the reſt of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces to the Acknowledgment of the <hi>Engliſh Republick, viz</hi> to give unto <hi>Ceſar,</hi> (that is, the preſent Poſſeſſor or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent) that which is <hi>Ceſars.</hi> Why did he not firſt make
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:112620:19"/>known this ſubtle ſolution of that Sophiſm to <hi>Spain, Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal, Venice, Florence, Genua?</hi> (<hi>France</hi> would fain come on too.) Did they underſtand the <hi>Date Caeſari</hi> thus? we had more reaſon for it.</p>
                  <p>As for thoſe other allegations, taken out of ſeveral Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, I ſhall direct him to infinite other Sermons, that were and are daily made in the behalf of the Parliament. The <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerers,</hi> and others wreſting of the Scriptures, like a Noſe of wax to ſerve their turns, is a kind of Prophanation.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Memorandums</hi> he calls <hi>Monſtrous things.</hi> A bold expreſſion. They contain the very words, ſet down in the <hi>Treaty</hi> of <hi>Anno</hi> 1495. and conſequently the <hi>States</hi> own words, delivered unto the <hi>Engliſh Ambaſſadors, May</hi> 2 laſt, which are not monſtrous, but grounded on very weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Reaſon. For, we do plainly find, that for divers years now all along, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scots</hi> Malignants, do not only ſeek to imbroil us in war, but labour likewiſe daily here to reduce us again under the ſubjection or Guardianſhip of the young Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> that needs a Guardian himſelf: So that it ſeems <hi>Lex Julia de ambitu,</hi> lies aſleep. Otherwiſe this State ought to rid themſelves of thoſe ſtrangers, that ſeek to obtrude a new Domination upon us. And the <hi>Engliſh</hi> deſerve our thanks, for having reacht forth their helping hand thus unto us.</p>
                  <p>In the Rear now our <hi>Anſwerer</hi> falls upon the thirty ſix Articles, and ſays, That the ſame do prejudice or hinder his Kings Right to the Crown of <hi>England.</hi> All the Kings and Potentates, which acknowledge <hi>England</hi> a Republick, do in effect the ſame thing: But indeed neither any of thoſe Kings and Potentates, nor we our ſelves, but the Kings ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> evill Councellors, or Proceedings, are the cauſe of all this. When the <hi>Anſerer,</hi> the reſt of his partners, the <hi>Scots</hi> and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanters, have hurried their Waggon into precipices of ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, it is paſt our redreſs. To enter into <hi>alliance</hi> againſt thoſe that go about to ruine our <hi>Commerce,</hi> and bereave us of our <hi>Freedom,</hi> as much as in them lies, is both neceſſary and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable. If ſome will needs live under a <hi>King,</hi> let them; as for our parts, we are reſolved by Gods help, to maintain our <hi>Freedom.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:112620:20"/>
                  <p>A League with <hi>England</hi> will not bring us into a Labyrinth, nor make us ſubjects of Depradation and Slavery; but free and ſecure us from both.</p>
                  <p>The Reſolutions of <hi>Neutrality,</hi> which he mentioneth, are limited with conditions; in caſe the <hi>Scots, Iriſh,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Pirats, perform <hi>Neutrality to us alſo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>All the former alliances are between the Nations; ſo their Lord ſhips the States underſtand it; ſo alſo do all the Kings and Potentates underſtand it, that Treat here with the States upon the ancient Treaties, as made in thoſe times under the name of the Duke of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> and <hi>Austria.</hi> The <hi>Anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer</hi> himſelf implies as much above, where he takes the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty vvith Duke <hi>Philip, Anno</hi> 1495. as made with their Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips the <hi>States;</hi> and ſo likewiſe the renued Treaty with <hi>Scotland,</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 1594. which Queen <hi>Mary</hi> had made, as Governeſs in the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> and the King of <hi>Scotland</hi> notwithſtanding renued it with their Lordſhips <hi>Non populi propter Regem ſed Rex propter populu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Kings &amp; Princes enter into Treaties, as Repreſenters of the People, for the peoples ſake. This Kings forefathers were contented with the Crown of <hi>Scotland.</hi> It grieves the <hi>Scots</hi> to ſee themſelvs involved in war about a quarrel that doth not concern them; but only for the Kings ſake, who by Pr. <hi>Rupert,</hi> and by other Pyratical ſhips and other ways, plaguing and provoking the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> did force them at laſt, to fall with an Army into <hi>Scotland,</hi> for to prevent that Kings falling into <hi>England.</hi> Even ſo did the great <hi>Guſtave</hi> of <hi>Sweden;</hi> he came with an Army in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Pruſſia,</hi> and forced the King of <hi>Poland</hi> his Couſen, to relinquiſh his pretenſions to the Crown of <hi>Sweden.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To conclude, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> well knowing, that the <hi>Scots</hi> joyned with <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fugitives, and <hi>Malignants,</hi> ſeek nothing but on the one ſide to ingage us againſt the parliament, or to make us ſtill ſubject to their depradations; and on the other ſide, to bring us again under the ſubjection of the Prince of <hi>Orange:</hi> Therefore they very lovingly came and invited us to mutual union, to prevent both the one and the other.</p>
                  <p>This, in effect, is the Sum and Truth of the Buſineſs.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:112620:20"/>
                  <head>AN ADDITIONALL REPLY TO All the pretended Arguments, falſ Inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Slanders, ſet forth in the Printed Anſwer OF <hi>MACK-DONNELL</hi> the <hi>Scotiſh</hi> RESIDENT, To the Propoſitions of the Ambaſſadors of the Common-wealth of <hi>ENGLAND; Preſented at the</hi> Hague, <hi>March</hi> 30/20. 1651:</head>
                  <div type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> The Neceſsity, Nature, and ſeveral Forms of Ambaſſy, ſtated.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T being impoſſible to preſerve Intercourſe and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity betwixt Nations, for their mutual weal and ſafety, without the intervention of ſuch a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or perſons, that may repreſent the ſenſe of either, ſo as to beget a right underſtanding betwixt them: And becauſe if the Supremacy be delegated or inveſted in one <hi>ſingle Perſon</hi> (whether a <hi>King, Duke,</hi> or <hi>Emperour</hi>) it were for many reaſons moſt inconvenient that he ſhould quit his Charge at home to treat perſonally abroad in <hi>foràin Parts;</hi> Or if the Supremacy be intruſted in the hands of <hi>divers Perſons,</hi> it were abſurd to imagine they ſhould all undertake a Voiage upon the like occaſion: Therefore it muſt needs be obvious to every mans reaſon, how great a neceſſity lies upon the Nations of the world, to make choice of ſome intermedial Perſon or Perſons, to be commiſſiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with full Power, and ſent abroad with ſuch Iuſtructions,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:112620:21"/>as may inable them, on the behalf of their reſpective Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, to confer and debate with forain States and Princes, of ſuch matters as tend to mutual Commerce and Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. <hi>Without ſuch a courſe as this,</hi> ſaith <hi>Petrus Aerodius</hi> (an old Author) <hi>no League can be made, nor any thing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined touching Peace or War; Enmities would prove im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal; Murthers, Violence, and Treachery, would perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally alarm the world with new Combustions.</hi> Hence it is, that in regard of the neceſſary uſe of ſuch Miniſters, and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard they repreſent the Majeſty of the State that ſends; them, a kind of <hi>ſanctity</hi> hath been annexed to their Perſons; they have in all Ages and Nations been had in ſpecial Veneration, indulged with large Priviledges and Immunities, even among the <hi>Heathen,</hi> and ſecured from the reach of <hi>violation,</hi> by as high a reverence as they paid to their very Gods and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, as may be ſeen in an Epiſtle of King <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donian,</hi> to the people of <hi>Athens. A Legat</hi> or <hi>Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſador</hi> is</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>Sanctum populis per ſaecula nomen:</label>
                     </p>
                     <p>As for the ſeveral Forms of <hi>Ambaſſy,</hi> or <hi>Ambaſſadors,</hi> though they paſs by divers names, yet they are ſpecifically one and the ſame <hi>Office</hi> or <hi>Function,</hi> having all the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, aim, or end; which is, to tranſact affairs abroad, for the good of the Common-wealth, according to the directions of thoſe that ſend them. In ancient time, a <hi>Legat</hi> or <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador,</hi> many times paſſed under the name of an <hi>Orator;</hi> according to that of <hi>Virgil</hi> 11. <hi>Aeneid.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>Jámque Oratores aderant ex urbe Latinâ.</label>
                     </p>
                     <p>And he uſually retained this name, either from the nature of his imploiment, in caſe he were ſent to deſire or depre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate any matter, or elſe from his <hi>Eloquence,</hi> which is the prime requiſit and glory of an <hi>Ambaſſador.</hi> The other uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al name of old, was that which the <hi>Pope</hi> ſtill retains, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Nuntio,</hi> which in <hi>Engliſh</hi> is a <hi>Meſſenger,</hi> according to that of <hi>Livy, lib.</hi> 34. <hi>Rhodios Nuntios in Orbe terrarum ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitria belli paciſque agere,</hi> which was ſpoken in contempt of the <hi>Rhodians,</hi> or rather indignation, that ſo inconſiderable a people ſhould be ſo buſie and medling; for, thoſe uſually
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:112620:21"/>they called <hi>Meſſengers,</hi> that were ſent from ſuch as either were not acknowledged Supream in power, or were but an inferiour Nation, or who came with ſmall pomp about matters of the leſſer concernment; or for the delivery of ſome diſpatches, about which they made no long ſtay.</p>
                     <p>But thoſe old titles being antiquated, we have new a ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of new ones, which are thus divided, according to the peſent cuſtom of Nations, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Agent,</hi> or <hi>Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor</hi> in ordinary, and the <hi>Ambaſſador</hi> extraordinary: both which, are one and the ſame in effect, differing only in pomp and ſplendor, but equal in priviledge. The Agent or Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador in ordinary, is uſually a perſon eminent for prudence; one that undertakes and performs the Ambaſſy with leſs out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward oſtentation; who if he be Commiſſionated to reſide with any <hi>Prince</hi> or <hi>Republick,</hi> is then called a <hi>Reſident.</hi> But this <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſident</hi> being for the moſt part as a <hi>Spy,</hi> to pry into the Affairs of thoſe to whom he is ſent, it were far better if that cuſtom of <hi>Reſidence</hi> were rather exploded, then continued any longer, it tending more to the prejudice, then the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of Nations. But of all others, the <hi>Reſident</hi> ought to be avoided, and not admitted in new and unſetled ſtates and Commonweals, if they mean to be ſafe, or preſerve their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation. For this cauſe it was, and in this caſe, that of old, Ambaſſadors had a retinue aſſigned them by the State where they reſided, under pretence of honour and reſpect to their Ambaſſy, but really to keep an eye over them; and ſo ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they could not ſo much as drink, or do any other neceſſary, but with the privity of theſe Attendants. <hi>Procop. l.</hi> 1. <hi>de Bello Goth.</hi> It was the ſame reaſon alſo, wherefore our <hi>Henry</hi> 7. cared ſo little for their company here in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> at the beginning of his unſetled Government: And queſtionleſs, it was in him a moſt notable point of Prudence; in all parallel caſes moſt worthy of imitation. Now he whom we call the extraordinary Ambaſſador, is (for the moſt part) a Perſon of ſome higher rank and intereſt in the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and therefore a far greater ſtipend and retinue is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned him, to uphold a Majeſtick Port, anſwerable to his own Quality, and for the honour of his Nation. The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:112620:22"/>(according to the common acception) are ſtyled <hi>ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Ambaſſadors, Agents,</hi> and <hi>Reſidents;</hi> the later <hi>Extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary,</hi> ſent uſually upon eminent and extraordinary occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Thus you ſee all the difference betwixt them is onely extrinſecal and formal, in reſpect of <hi>Ceremony;</hi> but <hi>de Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> according to the nature and end of the thing, they have the ſame intrinſecal value, and an equal right to the ſame im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities and priviledges. An example of the former wee have in the late Agencies of thoſe two Learned, but unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate Gentlemen, Doctor <hi>Doriſla,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Anthony Aſhcam,</hi> the one moſt barbarouſly aſſaſſinated in <hi>Holland,</hi> the other in <hi>Spain.</hi> And of the later, in the late ſolemn Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſy into <hi>Holland,</hi> performed by two Honourable perſons, the one being Lord Chief Juſtice of the Common Pleas, but both of the <hi>Parliamentary</hi> or <hi>Senatorian</hi> Order. Now if you would know the reaſon why we have thus briefly diſcuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Point of Ambaſſy under the ſeveral <hi>Forms,</hi> it is part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for Method ſake, as an Introduction to the other Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters which follow; but eſpecially to let both the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>Spaniard</hi> underſtand, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> have as much reaſon to expect juſtice and ſatisfaction for the butcheries of their two Agents, as if they had appeared in as glorious and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn an Equipage, as the greateſt Ambaſſadors in the world. And truly, their expectations might be the more heightned in this particular to hear from the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> in regard the matter hath been ſo plainly laid open by a Doctor of their own, of no mean rank and abilities, by name <hi>Don Auguſtin de Hierro,</hi> Knight of the Order of <hi>Calatrava,</hi> and <hi>Fiſcal</hi> (or Attorney General) of the Councel Royal, in a <hi>Charge</hi> by him exhibited againſt the Murtherers of Maſter <hi>Aſhcam;</hi> in which Charge, he thus determins it: <hi>That whether the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſent lately by the Parliament of</hi> England, <hi>was an</hi> Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador, <hi>an</hi> Agent, <hi>or</hi> Reſident, <hi>as the Murtherers term him, or moſt properly an</hi>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">Maſter <hi>Aſhcam</hi> was <hi>verus Lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius.</hi>
                        </note> Orator, (<hi>for, he came</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to deprecate Peace.) Or, whether he were all theſe, or any of theſe, it matters not; for, any of theſe may ſtyle him a</hi> Legat, <hi>&amp; make him deſerv that title; and the ſame ſecurity is due unto all thoſe titles,</hi>
                        <pb n="37" facs="tcp:112620:22"/>the ſame <hi>Priviledge,</hi> the ſame <hi>Immunity.</hi> And therefore, ſince the ſame Doctor hath alſo very clearly proved, that the <hi>Church</hi> cannot give <hi>ſanctuary</hi> to the Murtherers of the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of <hi>Publick Miniſters,</hi> (who are all equall in point of indemnity) the more highly it reflects upon <hi>Spain,</hi> that the <hi>Rights of Ambaſſadors</hi> ſhould receive ſo high a violation, and yet that there ſhould have been ſo long a delay of juſtice (up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an unjuſtifiable pretence) againſt Maſter <hi>Aſcham</hi>'s Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> That All Supream Powers in poſſeſſion <hi>(Jure vel Injuriâ)</hi> have a Right to ſend <hi>Agents</hi> or <hi>Ambaſſadors,</hi> to negotiate with Forain States and Princes.</head>
                     <p>BEcauſe, upon peruſal of the Printed <hi>Anſwerer,</hi> ſet forth by that <hi>Scot,</hi> who entitles himſelf the Lord <hi>Mac Don<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel,</hi> and Reſident of the King of Great <hi>Britain;</hi> it appears he will not vouchſafe our late Ambaſſadors at the <hi>Hague,</hi> to wear the ſtyle of <hi>Engliſh Ambaſſadors,</hi> but in his Title page diſdainfully calls them the <hi>Engliſh Ambaſſadors [as they ſtyle themſelves.]</hi> And in the beginning of his pretended Anſwer, nick-names them <hi>Ab-Legats</hi> in the <hi>Diminutive,</hi> and calls them <hi>pretended Ambaſſadors,</hi> as if they merited not the title of true Legats or Ambaſſadors; it cannot be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs therfore, to ſhew this <hi>Scot,</hi> and all the world, upon what frail terms, both his Lordſhip and the Reſidentſhip muſt needs ſtand, having ſo aiery a foundation to ſupport them, as his Maſter's Kingſhip of Great <hi>Britain;</hi> for we ſuppoſe it will be a hard matter for him to prove his Reſidentſhip, till his young <hi>Maſter</hi> can make good the Kingſhip; it being a Maxim received by all <hi>Civilians</hi> and <hi>Stateſmen,</hi> that the Right of Ambaſſy in all Countries, as do all the other Rights
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:112620:23"/>of <hi>Supremacy,</hi> ever follow ſuch as are in poſſeſſion. <hi>Hugo Grotius (lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de Jur. bel. cap.</hi> 18.) is very poſitive to this purpoſe, where he tells you, <hi>Reges qui bello ſolenni victi, reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nóque exuti ſunt, cum alis Regni bonis &amp; jus Legandi per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diderunt,</hi> that is, <hi>Kings who ſubmit their Fortunes to the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of a ſet-war, and then are driven out of the kingdome by force of arms, as they forfeit all other right of ſoveraignty, ſo alſo they loſe the very right of</hi> Ambaſſy. The reaſon to me is evident, becauſe the chief end of Ambaſſies (for the moſt part) is to make Contracts; and it is abſurd to imagin, that one man will contract with another, when it is not in the power of that other to make good the Contract, becauſe there is a third Power in poſſeſsion, which will hinder him from the performance. Now, all States and Princes mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the points of Ambaſſy and Negotiation by convenience and <hi>Reaſon of State.</hi> They conſider not what right or wrong is done to a <hi>Brother-Prince,</hi> in his title, in the great Revolu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ions of Government, but how to frame themſelves after the motion of the <hi>Great Wheel,</hi> as may tend moſt to the ſecurity of their own titles, and advantage of their own eſtates: For, if in ſtead of receiving Ambaſsies and Addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes from Forain Powers, they ſhould firſt require ſatisfaction touching the rights of thoſe which ſend, then the whole time of Princes would be ſpent in admitting mutual appeals to and from one another, to no purpoſe; ſince if that were admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, there would be no end of diſpute in the world touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing titles; which were they all ravelled to their Originals, would puzzle the ableſt head-pieces under Heaven to prove their equity and innocence in the Cradle. Very ſuitable hereunto is that paſſage of Cardinal <hi>D'Oſſat</hi> in one of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles, who tells you, <hi>That Princes, when Ambaſſadors are addreſt to them, never inform themſelves of the rights and titles of thoſe Princes from whom they are ſent; But whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they have poſſeſſion of the Forces and Power of thoſe places from whence the Ambaſſadors are imployed. For, it would be an endleſſe task, and require an infallible true Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the world (which is not to be made by man) if all the Ambaſſadors, before their Receptions, ſhould be obliged firſt
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:112620:23"/>to prove clearly to the world, the juſt right by which their maſters derive thoſe Titles and Jurisdictions, which they aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to themſelves.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thus far it ſeems by <hi>reaſon of State,</hi> that the <hi>right of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſy</hi> unqueſtionably follows ſuch only as are in poſſeſſion; let us confirm it farther (as briefly as may be) by teſtimonies of <hi>Writers,</hi> with the practiſes of States and princes, both ancient &amp; modern, who never uſed to inquire who they were that ſent, but whether the ſenders of an Ambaſſage were inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with a Power to command the places from whence they ſent: In this caſe, they always treat with the Power, but never diſpute it, well knowing few of their own Dominions have had an unqueſtionable beginning, <hi>Reſpectu primae Cauſae om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia Imperia legitima eſſe concedo, ſed ſi quer as de cauſis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termediis, &amp;c.</hi> All Governments (ſaith <hi>Bodin, l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 6.) are lawful in reſpect of the <hi>firſt cauſe,</hi> viz. <hi>God;</hi> but if we regard ſecondary cauſes, moſt Governments have had their founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon Force and Violence: which muſt needs be granted, conſidering how from time to time the <hi>Sword</hi> hath given Law to all the world. Whereupon, the <hi>Civilians,</hi> weighing, that the courſe of Government hath run altogether in this Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, have proportioned their Maxims more ſuitable to the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities and publick conveniencies of mankind, then ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory to the reaſons of private and particular men; becauſe, will they, nill they, ſuch muſt be concluded within the rules of ſubmiſſion, to what form of Government ſoever ſhall be ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by thoſe that cary the <hi>Sword.</hi> For, in this caſe, if a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, or Senate, that hath the <hi>Sword,</hi> ſhall reſolve one way, and thoſe that are <hi>un-armed,</hi> reſolve another, then there can be no Government at all, but all will be left at ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, to a continued ſucceſſion of diſcontents conteſts, and confuſions, which muſt needs end in the ruine of the <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>armed party.</hi> Wherefore, it is a <hi>Rule</hi> with them, <hi>That the ancient Majeſty of a Kingdom or Commonweal, continues no longer, if it be changed either by a greater Power, or by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the People:</hi> where you ſee, <hi>Force</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> are put in equall ballance with <hi>popular conſent,</hi> in relation to Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. And as if it were the beſt pedigree of <hi>Supremacy,</hi>
                        <pb n="40" facs="tcp:112620:24"/>they define the Supream Authority to be that which <hi>holds claim from God and the Sword; and therefore is as it were the Authour of its own Original, without dependance on any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; ſo that</hi> (ſay that) <hi>every Commonwealth, be it never ſo ſmall, which acknowledges no Superiour, but God and the Sword, hath a right of Majeſty, or Political Supremacy.</hi> So ſaith <hi>Beſoldus, de Juribus Majeſt. cap.</hi> 1. <hi>Arniſaeus, de Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſt. cap.</hi> 1. and <hi>Cammonus de Majeſt. Diſput.</hi> 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 70.75. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with many others.</p>
                     <p>Seeing therefore, that an uncontrolable Power of the <hi>ſword,</hi> in plenary poſſeſſion of any Nation, inſtates him or them whoſ <hi>Sword</hi> it is, w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> all the rights of Majeſty, much more then may they be claimed by the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> to whom God hath given a commanding Sword, which they lawfully hold in the behalf, and by conſent of the people. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore queſtionleſs, no State, or Prince, where he ſeeth ſuch an eſtabliſhed Power, can in reaſon queſtion thoſe rights, or pretend ground not to own the Power, as in all other rights, ſo more eſpecially in the <hi>right of Ambaſſy,</hi> which is one of the faireſt Flowers in the Garland of <hi>Majeſty.</hi> For, (as it hath been obſerved by the <hi>Oracle</hi> of our Laws, 4. <hi>Inſtit. c.</hi> 26.) they, and none but they, who enjoy the rights of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, or Supremacy, have a right of Ambaſſy. <hi>It muſt be from a Soveraign, to a Soveraign Power and Authority.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thus far now, our <hi>Aſſertion ſtands unqueſtionable;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, for illuſtration, it muſt needs be much more clear, if we conſider, that the benefit <hi>of Ambaſſy</hi> hath been often al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, even to ſuch as were not ſolely Supream, nor in the plenary poſſeſsion of any Nation. Thus in a Nation divided by Civil War, where the <hi>Supream Power</hi> is in Controverſie, both the Parties are allowed an equal right of Ambaſſy, by <hi>Hugo Grotius, l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 18. Thus in a popular diviſion at <hi>Syra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſa,</hi> the one Party within the City ſent an Ambaſſage to the other Party without, under the command of <hi>Andronodorus.</hi> The like was done by <hi>Caius Manlius,</hi> one of <hi>Catiline</hi>'s Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, to Q. <hi>Martins;</hi> and by <hi>Brutus</hi> and <hi>Caſſius</hi> to <hi>Lepi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> and <hi>Antony, Livius, l.</hi> 14. <hi>Saluſt Catil.</hi> who give them that were ſent the name of <hi>Legats,</hi> which were the ſame that
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:112620:24"/>we now call <hi>Agents</hi> and <hi>Ambaſſadors.</hi> Alſo, according to this Rule, during the late Conteſt here betwixt King and Parliament, it was, that the <hi>Hollander</hi> made no ſcruple to entertain <hi>Agents</hi> equally from both the Parties. Nor hath this Priviledge been allowed thoſe only, who in National ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, have had ſome tolerable pretence to a formal Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; but hath been indulged alſo to meer <hi>Out-Laws,</hi> ſuch as the <hi>Montaneers</hi> in the <hi>Alps,</hi> the <hi>Aſſaſſins</hi> of old, the <hi>Pickeroons</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> the <hi>Banditi</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> the <hi>Tories</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the <hi>Moſſe-Troopers</hi> in the Marches between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland.</hi> Q. <hi>Curtius, lib.</hi> 7. tels us of twenty thouſand ſuch Fellows, that were got into a Body to make Head againſt <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, and it came to a Fight, in which <hi>Alexander</hi> himſelf being wounded in the <hi>Forlorn,</hi> it came to a Parley. <hi>Itaque poſtero die miſerunt Legatos ad Regem.</hi> Whereupon, the next day they ſent Ambaſſadors to the King, who received them with all Ceremony, and cauſed them to ſit in his preſence. This were the more to be admired, but that we find <hi>Ceſar</hi> himſelf, <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>bell. civ.</hi> giving the like honour to thoſe <hi>Fugitives,</hi> that lurked in the Straits and Paſſes of the <hi>Pyrenaean</hi> Mountains, and affirming it lawful. Yet queſtionleſs, theſe inſtances are not to bee drawn into cuſtom, but may be imitated and approved, only upon the like occaſional accidents, and emergents of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity.</p>
                     <p>How ever, in regard ſome have openly in Print indeavoured to abridge us in <hi>England</hi> of our right and intereſt in this particular, it is requiſit we ſhould draw the Lines of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſy,</hi> in its utmoſt Extent and Latitude, that our Inferences and Inductions may ariſe the more eaſie: For, if they who upon the occaſion of a <hi>National Rupture,</hi> can (at the moſt) lay claim to no more but the name of a <hi>Party,</hi> have been, and are admitted into a participation of this right by States and Princes: and if ſo bee, that an irregular number of <hi>Out-Laws,</hi> and <hi>Renegade</hi>'s, formed into a formidable Body, have been received likewiſe into the ſame Priviledge by the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Monarchs, then <hi>à minori ad majus,</hi> the Argument muſt needs hold good as to thoſe in <hi>England,</hi> who are actually,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:112620:25"/>and juſtly inveſted with the Supream Power, and ſetled in the Nobleſt form. If ſcattered Recollections of Fugitives, Male-Contents, and frighted Remnants, have aſſumed this honour to themſelves much more may this Noble Nation of <hi>England,</hi> who though ſhe grew old, crooked, and defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, under the preſſures and oppreſsions of ſucceſsive Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, yet having ſhaken them off, baffled them beyond re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, and ſetled her ſelf in the condition of a Soveraign <hi>Free State,</hi> ſeems now to renue her Age again like the <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle,</hi> under the ſweet Influences of <hi>Liberty.</hi> She is now her ſelf, in full poſſeſsion of her own; therefore let the world know in this caſe ſhe underſtands, that <hi>Poſſeſſion is more then eleven points of the Law.</hi> For, why was it, that the late King of <hi>England</hi> (as one obſerves) having ſworn a League with the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> expreſly alſo as he was King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> did notwithſtanding receive divers Ambaſſadors from the new King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> yet was not judged, either in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> or <hi>Spain,</hi> to have broken his former Oath and League? Why was it (I ſay) but only to ſhew that Contracts and Oaths made betwixt <hi>Political</hi> perſons, are made in a <hi>Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> ſenſe, <hi>viz.</hi> with a <hi>tacit condition</hi> of holding their Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions? Theſe being gon, their Publick Relations and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments immediatly expire. How came it to paſſe that the <hi>Spaniard</hi> being driven out of the <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> and they by him declared Rebels, that yet they aſſuming to themſelves a <hi>right of Ambaſſy,</hi> had their Ambaſſadors ſo readily recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> but that both thoſe Princes well underſtood the lawfulneſs of the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that they had <hi>Jure Gentium,</hi> a right ſo to ſend, the <hi>Spaniard</hi> being diſpoſſeſſed there? It was the ſame reaſon too, that moved the <hi>Hollander</hi> to entertain Agents and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors from this State; before the death of the <hi>Tyrant,</hi> for that part which we then poſſeſſed; and ſince his death, for the whole now in poſſeſsion; in this acknowledging <hi>poſſeſſion</hi> a ſufficient ground for us to ſend, as for themſelves to receive our <hi>Ambaſſadors.</hi> The acknowledgements given us like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by the <hi>Ambaſſadors</hi> and <hi>Agents</hi> of <hi>Spain, Portugal, Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice, Florence,</hi> and <hi>Genoa,</hi> do declare the ſame.</p>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:112620:25"/>
                     <p>How then comes it to paſſe, that the name of a King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> hath been ſo rife among the <hi>Provinces,</hi> when they know the young <hi>Scot,</hi> is ſo farre from having a Foot in the Nobleſt part of <hi>Britain, England,</hi> that he is in a manner outed too in <hi>Scotland?</hi> What face too, (but that a <hi>Scot</hi> can face any thing) had this <hi>Scot,</hi> to deny our Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours the name of <hi>Engliſh Embaſſadours,</hi> and dubbe himſelf with a Title including a Right to <hi>England,</hi> where, his <hi>Maſter</hi> is never like to take the Air again, if (he have his due) unleſſe it be upon a <hi>Scaffold?</hi> But well may hee own the Title, when ſome of the <hi>Dutch</hi> have been ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to give it; yea, and under that name, doe more then give him Audience in their great <hi>Aſſembly.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Though they have many Bodies of <hi>Supremacy</hi> in the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands,</hi> yet we can acknowledge but <hi>one Supream</hi> in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> which is the <hi>Parliament;</hi> who being ſeated with full Power in the Peoples Right, can admit of no Competitor, nor permit any other Nation to impoſe one upon them, or diſpute their Title; but have reaſon to expect the ſame ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgements, that ever have been given to all Supream Powers in poſſeſſion, according to the <hi>Cuſtom of Nations;</hi> which if any Nation ſhall deny, or take occaſion to prevari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate in this point, they may in time underſtand, that <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> eſtabliſhed in this new Form, ſtands fully poſſeſt, not only by <hi>Right of Warre,</hi> but alſo according to the Right of Nature, and the ancient Laws and Cuſtomes of the Nation, being eminently adorned with all the Rights and Priviledges of the People; And that ſhe may now have as great abilities as ever, to aſſert her own Independency upon other Powers, and make her ſelf as conſiderable, either in enmity, or friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, as the proudeſt of her enemies.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="chapter">
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:112620:26"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> That Contracts and Alliances made betwixt <hi>States</hi> and <hi>Princes,</hi> doe not relate ſingly and perſonally to themſelves; but are made <hi>Jure Populi,</hi> in the behalf, and for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the People.</head>
                     <p>VVHere as it hath been alledged by the <hi>Reſident</hi> of the King of <hi>Scots,</hi> that the ancient and ſucceſſive Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts and Friendſhips betwixt <hi>England</hi> and the <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces,</hi> were made between them and the ſucceſſive Kings of <hi>England,</hi> and not with <hi>England</hi> otherwiſe conſidered; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he ſeems to affirm, that the validity of ſuch <hi>Contracts</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon, and expires with the perſons of the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> or with the <hi>Kingly Government,</hi> excluding the intereſt of the People from being Principal in them; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it cannot be inexpedient in that point, to manifeſt the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of this <hi>Scot,</hi> with the abſurdity of his <hi>Pretence,</hi> which ſo highly reflects upon the Majeſty and main Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the People.</p>
                     <p>For, without queſtion, it is to be underſtood, that as all the acts of Government ought to tend; ſo <hi>Governours</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, (by what names on titles ſoever they be called) are ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and intended only for the behalf and benefit of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Even <hi>Kings</hi> themſelves (notwithſtanding all their flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes) can arrogate nothing to their Perſons or Families, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from the Peoples Intereſt: For, a <hi>King</hi> is no more but a Creature of the People, by them created for their good; He is their ſervant, for which they give him a Sala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or Revenue, adorning him with ſplendid Titles of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and with all the Immunities, Priviledges, and Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatives of Government, which are no way inherent in his own Perſon or Family, but Ornaments beſtowed upon him, as the Peoples <hi>Livery,</hi> in reward of his ſervice.</p>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:112620:26"/>
                     <p>The truth of this very evidently appears in the <hi>Coronation-ſolemnities</hi> of Kings, which all the world over are the ſame in ſubſtance; and here in <hi>England</hi> the cuſtome was thus. Firſt, the agreement was made between the people and him that was to be entertained as their King: he was made acquainted with the work and ſervice of the Commonwealth, which was to regulate himſelfe and his Charge according to ſuch Lawes, (that is, ſuch Rules and Direction) as were or ſhould be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the people; and for the true performance of this an <hi>Oath</hi> was given him. Then the peoples conſent being asked, and had (which in old time here was wont to be demanded thrice) he was immediatly taken into the ſervice, and his <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very</hi> given him, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Royall Robes,</hi> the <hi>Sword,</hi> the <hi>Ring,</hi> the <hi>Scepter,</hi> and the <hi>Crown.</hi> This hath been the manner of admiſſion in <hi>England,</hi> moſt ſolemnly performed in receiving all the <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Queens</hi> from the days of <hi>Edward</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor, and long before: So that you ſee the relation wherein a <hi>King</hi> ſtands to the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> or <hi>Kingdom,</hi> is the ſame with that of a <hi>Servant</hi> to his <hi>Maſter;</hi> onely here is the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>privat Servants,</hi> That thoſe <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick honorary Servants</hi> having great honour confer'd upon them by the ſervice, are neceſſitated to maintain a large reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, and hold many in penſion and imployment, for which purpoſe they are allowed an extraordinary proportion of wages for their pains and expence in the performance of their duty, with a ſurpluſage of Subſidies or Supplies (many times) upon emergent occaſions of neceſſity.</p>
                     <p>This will further appeare if we conſider, that Kings <hi>hold</hi> not the poſſeſſion of a <hi>Kingdom</hi> by the ſame right as <hi>privat men</hi> doe their <hi>patrimonies.</hi> But yet it is not meant, as if Kings might not have poſſeſſions as other men have; for that is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowable, and hath been known here in <hi>England,</hi> as may be ſeen in the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, who from the Title of Duke of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> arriving to that of a <hi>King,</hi> enjoyed ſtill an inheritance in his own rights, as Duke of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> diſtinct from that of the <hi>Crown;</hi> and fearing the return of <hi>Lex talio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis</hi> upon himſelf and Family, that as he had diſpoſſeſſed others of the Kingdom, ſo his heirs might in time be diſpoſſeſſed
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:112620:27"/>again, therefore out of a prudent forecaſt he ſo ordered the matter, as to keep the Revenues of his <hi>Dutchie</hi> entire, and ſetled them in ſuch a way, as might preſerve them diſtinct from thoſe of the <hi>Crown,</hi> that in caſe any <hi>new Turn</hi> ſhould happen, his poſterity might (if they loſt the <hi>Kingſhip</hi>) know where to lay claim unto their <hi>ancient Patrimony.</hi> So then, we doe not deny but <hi>Kings</hi> may have poſſeſſions of their own, as well as other men, by inheritance or purchaſe; but thoſe which they hold in the right of the Kingdom, or Kingſhip are none of their own: The Patrimony of the <hi>Publick Exchequer</hi> is one thing, that of the <hi>Prince</hi> another, <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth held the Dutchy of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> as he was <hi>Henry,</hi> but the revenues of the Crown as he was the King, or publick ſervant of the Kingdom, not out of any peculiar propriety that he had in them. Nor can it in reaſon be imagined, that Kings ſhould have any thing of <hi>Propri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ty</hi> in what concerns the Kingdom, ſeeing in the firſt place the Regall dignity is no more but a <hi>Function,</hi> or <hi>Office,</hi> and he himſelf is but <hi>ſupremus officiarius,</hi> the higheſt Officer of the Kingdom, and you known, an Officer hath no right to what he is intruſted with for the benefit of another. Beſides, we know, that if any man be inveſted with a <hi>Propriety,</hi> he hath a power to alienate or ſel away his right; but Kings have no ſuch power as to alienate any part of the <hi>publick Revenue.</hi> Kings that have endevoured it in <hi>England,</hi> have been reſtrained; and not onely in that, but even in their immoderate expences, by Parliament. Nor is it ſo onely in <hi>England,</hi> but many laws have been made and renewed againſt it in <hi>Poland, Hungary, Scotland, France, Spain,</hi> and the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire;</hi> for we read what <hi>Wenceſlaus</hi> the Emperour, <hi>Malcolm</hi> of <hi>scotland,</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixth of <hi>France,</hi> ſuffered by at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting it, and what miſeries they brought thereby upon themſelves and the people. Innumerable teſtimonies might be produced againſt this power of <hi>Alienation</hi> in Kings, but that of <hi>Grotius, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de Jur. bel. c.</hi> 6. may the better paſs inſtead of all the reſt, in regard he is in moſt other particulars a little too rank of the <hi>Royaliſt. Patrimonium populi, cujus fructus deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nati ſunt, ad ſuſtentanda reipub. aut regia dignitatis onera, à regibus alienari, nec in totum, nec in partem poteſt. The patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:112620:27"/>of the people</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>whoſe revenues are appointed to eaſe the burthens of the Commonwealth, and ſupport the Recall dignity, cannot be alienated by Kings, either whole, or in part. Num &amp; in hoc jus majus fructuario non habent. For in this, (viz.</hi> the peoples publick Patrimony) <hi>they have no more then the right of an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſu-fructuary,</hi> who indeed receives the rents and profits, but hath no propriety in the lands.</p>
                     <p>Seeing now it appears that a King is no more but <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, the <hi>Ordinance of man,</hi> (a creature of mans making, as is to be inferred from the words of St. <hi>Peter;</hi>) ſeeing he is but a ſervant to the people, bargains with them to doe their work according to Laws (or Directions) &amp; to that end wears their <hi>Livery,</hi> and receives <hi>wages</hi> from them; ſeeing alſo that the right and propriety of the Kingdom remains in the people, not in him; and that the moſt which can be made of him, is but an <hi>Officer,</hi> or an <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſu-fructuary,</hi> one that hath no right in what he poſſeſſeth, ſave onely to receive the Profi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s, or Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues, in lieu of ſervice to be done for ſome other, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Community;</hi> then it may plainly be inferred, that the ends of <hi>Kingly Government,</hi> and conſequently all the acts of it, doe in no wiſe relate to the Perſon, Kingſhip, or Family of any King, but are terminated <hi>jure populi,</hi> in the right or behalf, and for the benefit of the people.</p>
                     <p>Thus far our <hi>Aſſertion</hi> ſtands undeniable; and therfore for application of it to the preſent matter in queſtion between us the <hi>Scottiſh Reſident,</hi> let us conſider, that if Kings are not for themſelves, but for the people, if they be Kings <hi>publico ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> in the peoples right, not in any particular perſonall qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of their own, then it merrily follows, That as the <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,</hi> ſo all the <hi>Acts</hi> of Government, and conſequently the making Peace or Warre, the allaying of enmities, the making Contracts and Alliances with forein States and Princes, are founded and concluded in the <hi>right of the people.</hi> It is they which treat, contract, &amp; confederate, only they agree that he ſhal tranſact and ſign it: The power is originally, really, and <hi>fundamentally</hi> in themſelves; it is but <hi>Miniſterially</hi> in the <hi>King,</hi> as a <hi>Publick ſervant;</hi> it is for the publick benefit, not his own privat, that he is intruſted to make a <hi>Contract;</hi> ſo that
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:112620:28"/>whether you conſider the publick relation he ſtands in, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which he can be no king, nor contract, nor do any other act of Government. Or whether you conſider the publick end and ſcope of the <hi>Contract,</hi> it muſt needs follow, that his own particular, or the intereſt of his <hi>Family,</hi> cannot be ſeparatly or ſingly concerned in the buſineſs, though it run in his name, ſeeing all is done by the right, and for the good of the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But our <hi>Scotch Reſident</hi> alledges out of <hi>Grotius,</hi> l, 2. c. 16. <hi>That a league made with a King holds firm to him, though he be driven by his ſubjects out of the Kingdom: For the right of the Kingdom remains with him, though he have loſt the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion,</hi> according to that of <hi>Lucan</hi>
                        <q>
                           <l>— Non unquam perdidit ordo</l>
                           <l>Mutato ſua jura loco.—</l>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>To this I anſwer in the <hi>firſt</hi> place; that if you conſider what is ſaid before, it muſt be granted that the right and propriety of a Kingdom remains in the people alwayes, be the King in or out of poſſeſſion. <hi>Secondly,</hi> it is much to be wondred that <hi>Grotius</hi> ſhould ſo farre forget himſelfe, as in this place to ſet down a poſition quite contrary to what he affirms in another, viz. <hi>c.</hi> 18. in that inſtance before cited, where he ſaith, <hi>That Kings, who ſubmit their fortunes to the tryall of a ſet-warre, and then are driven out by force of Arms, doe not onely loſe the right of Ambaſſy, but all other rights of Soveraignty.</hi> And if ſo, then without queſtion alſo a King loſeth all claim or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to any <hi>Forein Contracts</hi> or <hi>Alliances</hi> made with him, in the behalf of the Kingdom while he ſtood poſſeſſed: For by the ſame reaſon that he loſeth or forfeits one right, he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth all.</p>
                     <p>Beſides, in another place (<hi>viz lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 18.) he enume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates no leſſe then ſeven or eight caſts, wherein a King may forfeit, and be juſtly driven out of his Kingly intereſt and Kingdom; As in caſe a King aſſume more to himſelfe then of right belongs to him: Or in caſe he infringe thoſe lawes that he was ſworn to: Or incroach upon the Senaticall part and right of the people: Or if he relinquiſh the Helm of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment: Or give over the protection of the people: Or
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:112620:28"/>make warre againſt them: Or behave himſelfe as a Tyrant or publick enemy of the Nation. In all theſe <hi>Caſes, Grotius</hi> grants, that a King may juſtly be deprived; and not any of theſe, but might be verified upon the late King of <hi>England,</hi> and his Son the <hi>Young Pretender;</hi> who not onely loſt all Right, as being the Son of ſuch a <hi>Father;</hi> but by tracing him actually in the ſame ſteps of enmity, hath made the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture compleat, both for himſelf and the whole family: whereby, as he loſes all other intereſts, ſo without queſtion, his intereſt in all thoſe forein leagues and contracts, that were made with his <hi>Father</hi> while he was in poſſeſſion.</p>
                     <p>But to return where we left; the rights and acts of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment (as we have proved) being properly the intereſt and acts of the <hi>Community</hi> or <hi>People,</hi> and relate no farther to the <hi>King,</hi> than as a <hi>delegated Perſon,</hi> a <hi>Deputy</hi> or <hi>Truſtee,</hi> to treat and tranſact in their behalf; then, without queſtion, when this Officer the <hi>King,</hi> ſhall either for male-adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or treachery in his truſt, be put to death, or baniſhed, with his whole family, the Treaties, Contracts, and Alliances, made in his name with any <hi>Forain State,</hi> muſt needs continue in full force and power, to all intents and purpoſes, as long as the People and Community are in being, whoſe Contracts they are. To this accords that of <hi>Grotius</hi> likewiſe, l. 2. c. 15. <hi>Si cum Rege contractum ſit, non ſtatim perſonale erit cenſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum foedus,</hi> i.e. If a League be made with a King, it muſt not be preſently looked upon as a <hi>perſonal League.</hi> For, as he ſaith in the ſame place, after <hi>Pedius</hi> and <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lpian, plerumque perſona pacto inſeritur, non ut perſonable pactum fiat, ſedut de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtretur cum quo pactum eſt.</hi> The perſon of the Prince is uſually mentioned in the League, not that the League ſhould become perſonal, but only to ſhew with whom it was made. But it may be objected, that the League with <hi>Holland,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends not only to the King, but to his Succeſſors alſo. 'Tis true, it doth hold, as to the ſucceſſion; that is, as long as the ſucceſſion holds; for, <hi>Leagues</hi> muſt hold to the perſons of Princes and their ſucceſſors, as all other <hi>Political Compacts</hi> between them do, <hi>viz.</hi> with a tacit condition of <hi>holding their poſſeſſions.</hi> If the King of <hi>Scots</hi> can with the peoples con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, make good his ſucceſſion in <hi>England,</hi> then he may lay
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:112620:29"/>claim to the Treaties made betwixt <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland;</hi> but in the mean time, Hee and his Family being driven out for their Tyranny, all the Right to thoſe Contracts is to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed by another Succeſſion and Form of Government, that is eſtabliſhed in the Right, and by Authority of the people.</p>
                     <p>Nor can this <hi>Alteration of Government</hi> any whit alter the Caſe, it being a right naturally inherent in all Nations, to alter their reſpective Governments (upon occaſion) into what form they pleaſe. As long as the people remain the ſame <hi>ſpecifical</hi> (I do not mean the ſame <hi>individual</hi>) people of <hi>England,</hi> that they were when the right of Treaty was uſed, and the Treaty with <hi>Holland</hi> made and ratified by the King in their behalf, ſo long the effects of the <hi>Treaty</hi> or <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> are in force, to the ſame ends and purpoſes that they were at firſt intended: <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith, by way of compariſon, <hi>Manet idem flumen, aqua tranſmiſſa eſt,</hi> the River remains the ſame, though the water paſs away; and <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> 3. <hi>lib. Pol c.</hi> 2. traceth him in the ſame quaint way of alluſion, like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the People to a River which retains its old name, and is ſaid to be the ſame that it was long ſince, though a continued ſucceſſion of new waters doe flow in the Channel; ſo the People that is now, is the ſame <hi>in ſpecie,</hi> that it was an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred or perhaps a thouſand years ſince, and is ſo called and reputed; except it loſe the name and eſtimate of a Nation, by being captivated and caried away from their Countrey, as the <hi>Jews</hi> were all in time from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the <hi>Holy Land;</hi> or inſlaved in their own Countrey by ſome Forain Power, that holds them in Vaſſalage, as the <hi>Olynthians</hi> were under <hi>Philip,</hi> the <hi>Thebans</hi> under his ſon <hi>Alexander,</hi> the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puans</hi> under the <hi>Romans;</hi> or as the old <hi>Britains</hi> were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Saxons,</hi> the <hi>Saxons</hi> under the <hi>Danes,</hi> and afterwards under the Tyranny of the <hi>Norman</hi> Conquerour: When their National Power and Authority is once extinct, they no longer retain their former intereſt, priviledge, or dignity. But none of theſe exceptions (bleſſed be God) can be verifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the people of <hi>England,</hi> who are ſeated <hi>pleno Jure,</hi> in their own fortunate Iſland, and eſtabliſhed now in a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter meaſure of Honour, Power, and Freedom, then ever we
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:112620:29"/>enjoyed for many hundred years before;
<q>Foelices nimiùm, bone ſi ſua nôrint.</q> And therefore, of neceſſity, they muſt be accounted <hi>ſpecifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally</hi> the ſame Nation or people, that they were, when the Treaties were made and concluded betwixt <hi>England</hi> and the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> though they be not the very ſame <hi>Individuall</hi> People and Government. <hi>No matter</hi> (ſaith <hi>Grotius,</hi> l. 2. c. 9.) <hi>how the Nation be governed, whether by a King, or by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, or by the multitude: For, the people of</hi> Rome <hi>remained the ſame ſtill, in the various changes of Government, under Kings, Conſuls, and Emperours.</hi> When the former is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct, a new form ever ſucceeds, with power to govern, act, and tranſact, in and for the behalfe of the people; who being ſtill the ſame, not tied to Forms, nor altered by Time, over-look all <hi>Circumstances,</hi> and lay hold upon the <hi>Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials</hi> of their Intereſt and Government, as they ſtand qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified, and related, both at home and abroad. And truly, it is very pleaſant to obſerve in this particular, how even <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> themſelves acknowledge as much in their Practiſes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards each other in the changes of Government: For, the Duke of <hi>Burgoin</hi> having concluded amity with <hi>England</hi> in the perſon of <hi>Henry</hi> the 6. no ſooner was <hi>Henry</hi> diſpoſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and <hi>Edward</hi> the 4. inveſted, but he immediatly renues the ſame League with <hi>England</hi> in the perſon of <hi>Edward:</hi> Afterwards, <hi>Edward</hi> hapning to be driven out, it was ſo brought about by <hi>Burgoin,</hi> that the Truce formerly conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded betwixt him and King <hi>Edward,</hi> ſhould in all things bee ratified and confirmed, the King's name onely changed to <hi>Henry.</hi> At length, <hi>Edward</hi> made ſhift to recover all again, and then <hi>Henry</hi> was once more dethroned; which was no ſooner done, but <hi>Burgoin</hi> ſent again a ſolemn Embaſſage, to renue the Treaty, and eſtabliſh a firm League with <hi>England</hi> in the perſon of <hi>Edward?</hi> It is to be obſerved likewiſe that during all theſe Changes, <hi>Ambaſſadors</hi> went to and fro, and all Forain Contracts and Alliances were kept entire, without the leaſt queſtion, on either ſide; which may ſerve to inform us of theſe two particulars; That in National quarrels about Title to Government, Princes uſe not to diſpute who is in
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:112620:30"/>the right, or wrong, but apply themſelves (without farther ſcruple) to the parties in poſſeſſion. And <hi>ſecondly,</hi> that however the <hi>Governours</hi> of a Countrey may be changed, yet all the points of <hi>Alliance</hi> and <hi>Contract,</hi> being centred in the right and benefit of the people, continue unchangeable and entire under every alteration. It were endleſs to reckon up all the examples that might be derived from the practiſes of States and Princes to confirm this particular; we might ſhew you how the matter of Government being in diſpute betwixt Queen <hi>Mary</hi> and her ſon <hi>James,</hi> (or rather his Guardians) though <hi>Mary</hi> were dethroned, and her <hi>Sons Guardians</hi> got the better, yet the amity betwixt us and <hi>Scotland</hi> continued firm, notwithſtanding the depoſition of the perſon of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry:</hi> But becauſe the <hi>Scottiſh Reſident</hi> ſeems to grant that Leagues may hold entire in State-Ruptures, though a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Prince be laid aſide, but not ſo, if the frame of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment be altered; therefore he may be pleaſed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that in the various revolutions of the <hi>Florentin</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, when the whole frame was changed, yet moſt of their old Alliances and Contracts were renued ſtill, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in full force and vigour, as well with the States and Princes of <hi>Italy,</hi> as thoſe of other Nations. And as for the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> though of late they boggled with us in the main, yet they would gladly have renued ſo much of the old Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties with the people of <hi>England,</hi> as might have ſerved their own turns, &amp; not have ingaged them too far; the reaſon why they kept off, ſeems not to have been from any ſtrength of Argument uſed by this <hi>Statizing Pretender;</hi> but they had a ſtronger Argument of their own, whoſe <hi>Premiſes</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion</hi> lay a long time in <hi>Scotland,</hi> from whence every Poſt they expected a reſolution.</p>
                     <p>I ſhall cloſe all with the teſtimony of that Learned <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Doctor <hi>Don Augustin de Hierro,</hi> Atturney General of the Councel Royal in <hi>Spain,</hi> &amp;c. produced by him in his late <hi>Charge</hi> againſt the Murtherers of Maſter <hi>Aſhcam;</hi> where inſiſting upon the point of Friendſhip betwixt <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> he proceeds thus: <q>That <hi>England</hi> (ſaith he) ſhould be our Friend <hi>in ſtatu quo nunc,</hi> and that Peace ſhould bee
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:112620:30"/>continued with her, proceeds from right; For, Peace is not only made with the <hi>King,</hi> but with the <hi>Kingdom</hi> alſo, and though the firſt expires, the laſt remains. For, put caſe, that Peace be concluded with a Country, without including the King, either b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> careleſneſs, or ſome other accident, yet the Peace ſtands good; For, ſo the <hi>Poliſh</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates anſwered the Emperour <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the ſecond. <hi>Faltando el Ray, ſe conſervan con el Reyno, i. e.</hi> the King failing, yet Peace is to be conſerved with the kingdom. So <hi>Bodin</hi> holds, and urgeth a pregnant example to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, <hi>lib. de repub. cap.</hi> 4. <hi>fol.</hi> 63. where he alledgeth the Anſwer which the Ambaſſadors of <hi>France,</hi> made to <hi>Edw.</hi> the 4. King of <hi>England,</hi> deſiring aid from <hi>France</hi> againſt ſome riſing ſubjects of his, that had driven him out of poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, and this deſire he preſſed by vertue of the League between them; Which Anſwer was, that the <hi>King of</hi> France <hi>could not help him, in regard the confederations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt</hi> France <hi>and</hi> England, <hi>were made betwixt the Kings and Kingdoms, ſo that though King</hi> Edward <hi>was diſpoſſeſſed therof, yet the league &amp; amity remained ſtil with the kingd. &amp; with the King Regnant.</hi> Juſt ſo, the Peace 'twixt the Kings and Kingdoms of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> though <hi>Charles Stuart</hi> the King be wanting, <hi>yet it may be kept intire with the Kingdom:</hi> And his Majeſty himſelf inſinuates ſo much unto us, continuing ſtill his Ambaſſador in <hi>England;</hi> For, when a Peace is eſtabliſhed 'twixt Kings and Kingdomes, People, Perſons and Vaſſals, though the King fail, and the Kingdom receive a differing Form of Government, yet the Peace holds good ſtill, becauſe it aimed principally at the people and perſons of both Nations; and upon theſe terms the Peace was renued 'twixt <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> in the year 1630.</q> as the <hi>French Mercury</hi> relates it.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Reſult</hi> of all then, out of the foregoing reaſons, te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies, and examples, will be undeniably this; that <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts</hi> made betwixt States and Princes, doe not relate ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and <hi>perſonally</hi> to themſelves, but are made <hi>Jure Populi,</hi> in the behalf, and for the good of the Community. Though Governors and their Families may fail, yet their Treaties are
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:112620:31"/>as eternal, as the peoples intereſt, which is their <hi>moving cauſe,</hi> and their <hi>ultimate end.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And therefore, as to our particular, it muſt undeniably follow, that thoſe former Treaties made betwixt our <hi>Kings</hi> and the <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> belong to us now of right, if we pleaſe to claim, or renue them, having been ratified at firſt, in reſpect only to the people of <hi>England.</hi> No King can lay any claim of this nature, but as he is an Officer of the people; For, that relation being once extinct, there remains no Foundation for any future pretences.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
                     <p>THE two former <hi>Chapters,</hi> being as the two <hi>Hinges,</hi> whereupon hangs the main of the Controverſie; and having therein vindicated the principal points of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples intereſt in <hi>England,</hi> our deſign in the next place is, briefly to refute all the petty falſhoods and inſinuations, which lie ſcattered here and there, in the pretended Anſwer of our <hi>Scottiſh Pretender.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>That which occurs in the firſt place, is this; where hee tells the States of the <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> that <hi>the Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of the preſent Governours in</hi> England, <hi>were very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable in thoſe days when the Treaties were made; and that they had neither part nor participation, in any of the favours and friendſhip afforded to the</hi> Netherlands: This he ſaith, <hi>by all circumſtances may ſtrongly be preſumed.</hi> A very ſtrong preſumption indeed, it muſt needs be, till he can name thoſe <hi>Circumſtances.</hi> The Parliaments of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> which were the Predeceſſours of our preſent <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours,</hi> were not ſo conſiderable indeed, as now they are, and will be, we ſhall eaſily grant; becauſe their glory and freedom was eclypſed by thoſe unbounded Prerogatives, which <hi>Kings</hi> and their Houſe of <hi>Peers,</hi> did uſurp unto themſelves, over the <hi>Commons,</hi> who naturally, really, and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:112620:31"/>properly, were to be eſteemed <hi>the Parliament;</hi> becauſe they only ſate, and repreſented the people in their rights; whereas the <hi>Lords</hi> ſate only in their own rights, or rather by vertue of that pretended <hi>right,</hi> which Kings (forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting whoſe ſervants they are, and for what end they were made) had arrogated unto themſelves, in and over the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: This was the reaſon, why the Commons of <hi>England</hi> became more inconſiderable then by right they ought to have been. Yet take them in their moſt inconſiderable ſtate, or in the loweſt ebb of their Fortunes, and we never ſee them ſo low, but we find them admitted as partners in enacting of Laws, and reputed as principal in granting <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidies,</hi> and other Supplies, for the neceſſities and ſupport of the <hi>Crown,</hi> inſomuch that no <hi>Aid-monies</hi> could be required of the people, but by the <hi>Commons</hi> conſent. In Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s time, they were brought low enough, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by her ſtrange proceeding againſt <hi>Wentworth,</hi> that was one of their Members; which (perhaps) had not been ſo tamely taken from a <hi>Prince,</hi> that had leſs influence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their affections: yet, as low as they were, the ancient Treaties betwixt <hi>Elizabeth</hi> and thoſe <hi>Provinces,</hi> were not made and renued; nor were the favours and ſupplies, both of men and money, afforded unto that State, but in the behalf of the <hi>Community,</hi> out of the Purſes of the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> in whoſe name and right they were granted: ſo that we leave the world to judge, how nearly thoſe <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> did concern the the <hi>Commons;</hi> and whether they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the undeniable <hi>Predeceſſors</hi> of the preſent Governours in <hi>England,</hi> did not both partake, and participate, yea, and were the <hi>Principall Party</hi> concerned in thoſe tokens of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and friendſhip, which were then ſont unto the <hi>Low-Country Provinces?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But to fright them from our friendſhip, he tells them a ſtrange Tale, <hi>How big we are grown with monſtrous myſteries of enlarging our Trade and Power.</hi> 'Tis more then probable, that <hi>England,</hi> in this new form, will improve its ſelf fat be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond its wonted wealth and intereſt; foraſmuch as for theſe many hundred years, it hath continued labouring and ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:112620:32"/>under the yoak of a <hi>Tyrant,</hi> ſo that it could not poſſibly arive to ſuch a height and meaſure of happineſſe, as it may now attain in a condition of <hi>Liberty.</hi> But why ſhould <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> happineſſe be counted an eye-fore to the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> as our <hi>Scot</hi> would have it? Surely the world is wide enough for them both; and queſtionleſſe, if <hi>England</hi> ſhall thrive (as the enemies of it feare) in this new form the <hi>Dutch</hi> will then ſee it much more concerned them (both in honor and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt) to have ſettled with us in the relation of a friend, then remain in a ſtate of neutrality. 'Tis but a crude ſuppoſition, that they ſhall loſe any thing by our <hi>Amity;</hi> but very proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble they may loſe much without it. Yet in another place he alledges to the <hi>States,</hi> that <hi>their Lordſhips having no enemy at preſent, will by uniting with us, involve themſelves in a laby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth.</hi> But their <hi>Lordſhips</hi> may be pleaſed rather to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, it were a ſtrange <hi>Wild-gooſe-chace,</hi> to be led about by the way of <hi>Scotland,</hi> to ſettle an intereſt for themſelves in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> upon the uncertain favour of a ſubtile <hi>Tyrant</hi> and his followers, who in times paſt at Court here were wont to dart the name of <hi>Rebell</hi> as freely at them, as they doe now againſt us; being men of oppoſite principles to <hi>Freedom,</hi> ſuch as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the very name of the <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces;</hi> And if the <hi>States</hi> pleaſe to remember the carriage of King <hi>James,</hi> they will find that he himſelf was of the ſame humor and opinion, and the firſt that ſet an edge upon the tongues of the <hi>Courti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</hi> In vain therefore doth this <hi>Reſident</hi> tell them, that their <hi>Lordſhips have no Enemy at preſent:</hi> For, however, our <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Fugitives</hi> and <hi>Deſperado's</hi> (for preſent ends) may ſeem to court them; yet if they had a while ſince regained poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in <hi>England,</hi> and ſhould the young <hi>Prince of Orange</hi> have lived to ſee it, it would have appeared to purpoſe, that they are the very worſt of all their enemies. How much more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure then had it been for their <hi>Lordſhips</hi> to have embraced the late offer of <hi>England</hi> in its preſent eſtabliſhment, as a ſure friend, then to depend upon the good will of a deceitful <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</hi> And whereas it is inſinuated, that a <hi>League</hi> with us would draw enmities upon them elſwhere, <hi>they having no ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my at preſent;</hi> it will concern them to remember, what a
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:112620:32"/>friend they have of the <hi>French,</hi> who onely gives faire words, but hates them mortally in heart, as appeares by the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all depredations made upon them at Sea, by thoſe of the <hi>French</hi> Nation. Alſo, it were worthy conſideration, upon what tickliſh termes they ſtand with <hi>Denmark</hi> and <hi>Sweden;</hi> and in manifeſt diſcontent (eſpecially) with <hi>Portugall.</hi> Not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of theſe will, or can, be more a friend or enemy, for the ſake of the King of <hi>Scotland:</hi> they are all ſwayed by their own <hi>intereſt,</hi> and accordingly meaſure both their love and hate, not out of reſpect to any ſingle Perſon or Family: Therefore it wil concern the <hi>States</hi> more rationally to weigh what advantages they might have reap't by an union with <hi>England;</hi> which had it been concluded upon ſuch terms as were offered, would have rendred them ſo conſiderable in the eyes of the world, that not any of all the <hi>Friendly Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> round about, but would have been the more inclined to continue their <hi>Pretences,</hi> and the leſſe apt to break them. Moſt abſurd therefore is that affirmation of the <hi>Scotiſh Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident,</hi> in ſaying, <hi>The States may promiſe themſelves more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, repute, and ſecurity in Commerce,</hi> England <hi>abiding a Kingdom, then being transform'd into a Republick:</hi> For, as a <hi>Kingdom,</hi> the actions both of <hi>James</hi> and <hi>Charls</hi> will tell them, Kings were no cordiall friends, nor indeed can they be; whereas being in the form of a <hi>Republick</hi> the <hi>Provinces</hi> (had they embraced our offers) might have been admitted into a neerer union and complication of intereſts, then ever they can hope for from a <hi>Monarchy.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>He tells us farther, there is a wide difference betwixt the <hi>Hollanders</hi> and us, in the <hi>manner of acquiring our Freedom,</hi> The <hi>Hollanders</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>were a free people time out of mind but we in</hi> England <hi>have been under Soveraign Kings for a thouſand years, and were bound to them by oaths.</hi> Beſides, he ſaith, the <hi>K. of Spain after a tedious warre of</hi> 80. <hi>years, hath declared the Provinces free, &amp;c. But the caſe is otherwiſe with us in</hi> England. To this we ſay, If the <hi>Hollanders</hi> have of old been a <hi>free people,</hi> ſo have we been in <hi>England,</hi> and both they and we in the ſame manner. They were of old un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Earls</hi> or <hi>Princes,</hi> but ſuch as were limited by the laws. <hi>Auctoritas Principum er at plurimis pro libertate legibus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitis
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:112620:33"/>definita,</hi> ſaith the Author <hi>de Statu Belgii</hi> 1650. So were we in <hi>England</hi> under Princes called <hi>Kings,</hi> but ſuch on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as were limited by lawes. It was a <hi>Politicall</hi> Kingſhip, not <hi>Deſpotick</hi> or <hi>Tyrannick,</hi> as may be ſeen in all our <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>books.</hi> Let one or two old inſtances ſerve for all. <hi>Bracton l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 16. <hi>Fletal.</hi> 1 <hi>c.</hi> 17. ſay, that the King of <hi>England hath the Law and the Parliament for his ſuperiors; and therfore if the King have the reins looſe, and be without a Bridle, they ought to bridle him:</hi> For (as <hi>Bracton</hi> ſaith again, l. 3. <hi>c.</hi> 9.) <hi>The King can do nothing but what the Law permits him.</hi> Thus only, and with this <hi>limitation implied,</hi> wee we ſworn to our <hi>Kings,</hi> as the <hi>Hollanders</hi> were firſt to their Earls, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to the King of <hi>Spain;</hi> but finding the <hi>Spaniard</hi> to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe them contrary to Law and Liberty, therefore they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived themſelves acquitted of their former <hi>Oaths. Et Philip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi, ſimul &amp; omnium Principum Imperium ejuravere,</hi> and (as our former <hi>Author</hi> ſaith) bound themſelves by a new Oath to abjure the Government not onely of <hi>Philip,</hi> but of all Princes for ever; which courſ exactly parallels our caſe here in <hi>England:</hi> all the difference now then, is onely in a circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Time; We have not had 80 years Warre to make good our <hi>Freedom;</hi> but (alas) this alters not the verity of the thing: For, as the Freedom of the <hi>provinces</hi> (being real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly free from the very firſt moment wherein they drave out <hi>Philip</hi>) did not depend upon the <hi>Spaniards</hi> acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſo neither doth ours upon the acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and declaration of <hi>Charls,</hi> or any future Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the <hi>Family.</hi> Yet notwithſtanding this, the <hi>Reſident</hi> ſaith, our caſe, in reference to the recovery of our <hi>Freedom,</hi> is no more like to the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> then <hi>Milk</hi> is like <hi>Ink.</hi> But for illuſtration, take this farther; were they oppreſſed in matter of <hi>Religion?</hi> So were we; tied up to ſtrange forms and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations. Were they crucified with an <hi>Inquiſition?</hi> So were we with a <hi>High Commiſſion.</hi> Were they ſqueezed with <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions?</hi> So were we; ſuch as <hi>Ship-money, Privy-ſeals, Coat and Conduct, Monopolies,</hi> and a thouſand other devices. Beſides, the <hi>Prieſts</hi> proclaimed at Court in their <hi>Sermons,</hi> that <hi>All was the Kings, no man had any propriety in what he poſſeſſed:</hi> ſo that the leſſe credit is to be given to the <hi>Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
                        <pb n="59" facs="tcp:112620:33"/>of thoſe pious <hi>Miniſters</hi> (as they are called) againſt the Parliament, whoſe partiall teſtimony is ſo much applauded by the <hi>Reſident of Scotland.</hi> Did <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi> endeavour (through his Agent <hi>D'Alva</hi>) to ſettle his Tyrannies over the <hi>Provinces</hi> by force of Arms? ſo did the late Tyrant <hi>Charls</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> firſt plot a war, and then ſet up his <hi>Standard,</hi> and put the Parliament upon the <hi>Defenſive,</hi> as appears by the whole <hi>Series</hi> of his Councels and Actions; whereto more credit is to be given, than to his Poſthume Book of <hi>Meditations,</hi> which the <hi>Reſident</hi> hath quoted with more af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection than diſcretion.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Laſtly,</hi> are our Proceedings in <hi>England</hi> diſtaſted by ſome of our neighbours, through the malice and miſ-repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our <hi>Engliſh Fugitives?</hi> So were thoſe of the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers,</hi> through the malicious ſubtilty of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents and Miniſters, who laboured to incenſe all <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> and draw the world about their ears, till <hi>Forain Princes</hi> came to have a right underſtanding of the buſineſs: So that you ſee Maſter <hi>Reſident</hi> might have ſpared his <hi>Milk</hi> and <hi>Ink</hi> too; for, <hi>nec Ovum ovo ſimilius;</hi> one Egge cannot more exactly reſemble another, than the caſe of <hi>England,</hi> in all particulars, doth that of <hi>Holland,</hi> in the manner of acquiring our <hi>Liberties</hi> and <hi>Freedoms.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Now he rails at our judging and beheading the late King, and baniſhing his Family, calling it <hi>abominable violence, and ſuch as the like was never heard of ſince the beginning of the world.</hi> Therfore, to rectifie the ignorance and malice of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and his <hi>deluded party</hi> in this particular, ſome few In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances and Examples ſhall be here inſerted, to ſhew, it is no new thing, that Kings have been, and may be deprived or puniſhed with death, for their crimes in Government. We read of <hi>Amon</hi> King of <hi>Judah,</hi> that was ſlain by a part of the people, <hi>becauſe he walked not in the way of the Lord;</hi> and though another part of the people were angry at it, and avenged his death upon thoſe that did it; yet without queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the execution was juſt, according to the Law of God, which was (without reſpect of perſons) that the <hi>Idolater</hi> ſhould die the death; and no doubt, the puniſhment had been inflicted by a Judicial Proceſs, had not ſo great a party
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:112620:34"/>of the people been addicted to his ways, &amp; oppoſed it: which oppoſition of their, is uſually the cauſe, in all caſes of this nature, why Kings are not to be attached, as well as other M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>efactors, by an ordinary courſe of Juſtice.</p>
                     <p>Conſider <hi>Ahab</hi> likewiſe, who though he were taken off himſelf by divine Juſtice in the battel at <hi>Ramoth-Gilead,</hi> and ſo eſcaped puniſhment by man for his idolatry and cruelty; yet it was executed afterward to the full by <hi>John,</hi> upon his Queen and the whole Family, who were utterly rooted out, and a bleſſing annexed to him and his heirs that performed the execution. But ſome may ſay, this fact was extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, being done by immediate command from God, and ſo not fit for ordinary imitation. Yet, for Anſwer, it is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, I ſay, that it had a Legal ground, <hi>viz.</hi> the ground of Gods ordinary judgement, which commanded, that all offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors of the ſame nature, ſhould die the death. Gods extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary command, being ſuperadded to his ordinary Law, doth (as to us) rather confirm then weaken the equity and juſtice of ſuch a proceeding. In like manner we read, that the whole people took <hi>Amaziah</hi> King of <hi>Judah,</hi> and ſlew him for his idolatry: whether they did it by a way of Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial proceſs, or not, is not material, but done it was: and if it were done without proceſs, then much more are they to he juſtified, that have the courage to imitate ſuch noble acts of Juſtice, by a ſolemn and ſerious proceeding. The like had been executed upon <hi>Joas,</hi> the father of <hi>Amaziah,</hi> by a part of the people, for his Murther and Apoſtacy. Profane ſtories, both ancient and modern, are full likewiſe to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. <hi>Romultes,</hi> the firſt King of <hi>Rome,</hi> was for his tyranny cut in pieces by the <hi>Senate;</hi> and <hi>Tarquin</hi> (their laſt King) was with his whole family, caſhiered, the form of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment changed, by the ſame power, and upon the ſame oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion. Many years after, <hi>Nero</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperour, was ſentenced to death by the <hi>Senate;</hi> which was not <hi>primum damnati Principis exemplum,</hi> as the <hi>Reſident</hi> alledges out of <hi>Suetonius.</hi> The <hi>Senate</hi> being afterward in time cowed down by <hi>Heliogabalus</hi> their Emperour, ſo that they could not take the ordinary courſe with him, uſed means by corrupting the ſoldiery, (upon whoſe ſtrength he depended) to put him to death.</p>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:112620:34"/>
                     <p>The two famous changes made in the Royal line of <hi>France,</hi> depend upon two ſuch noble pieces of Juſtice; executed upon their Kings; the firſt upon <hi>Childerick,</hi> the third King of <hi>France,</hi> who being judicially depoſed by the Nobility and Clergy in Parliament, the ſucceſſion was then cut off from the family of <hi>Pharamond,</hi> and confirmed to the race of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pin,</hi> till <hi>Charls</hi> of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> the laſt of <hi>Pepin</hi>'s race, was in the like manner chaſtiſed by Parliament, and the Crown tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated to the ſucceſſors of <hi>Hugh Capet,</hi> who hold the ſame to this day; though two of them likewiſe, <hi>viz. Lewis</hi> the third, and <hi>Charles le Groſs,</hi> have been judicially proceeded againſt in Parliament. And though the people were ſo tender to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, as not to put them to death; yet they were bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried alive, being mued up within the melancholy walls of ſome Monaſtery, or elſe cloſely confined within the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of <hi>Orleans.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In <hi>Spain</hi> too we read of <hi>Suintila, Don Alonſon,</hi> the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth, and <hi>Don Pedro,</hi> judicially proceeded againſt; the firſt by the fourth National Councel of <hi>Toleao;</hi> the ſecond by publick Act of the Eſtates of the Realm in the Town of <hi>Validolid;</hi> the third, by the Eſtates of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> all for their Tyrannical Government.</p>
                     <p>The like proceeding alſo was had againſt <hi>Don Sancho</hi> the ſecond of <hi>Portugal:</hi> alſo againſt <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Poland,</hi> that was King of <hi>France: Henry</hi> of <hi>Swethland: Chriſtiern</hi> of <hi>Denmark,</hi> and <hi>Wenceſlaus</hi> of <hi>Bohemia:</hi> as alſo <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond, and <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond of <hi>England.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Theſe laſt are mentioned by the <hi>Reſident</hi> himſelf; but that which he mainly inſiſts upon, is, that neither <hi>Chriſtiern, Wenceſlaus, Edward,</hi> nor <hi>Richard,</hi> were beheaded upon a <hi>Scaffold,</hi> as was the late Tyrant <hi>Charls.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>However, it is ſufficient they were judged more worthy of a <hi>Scaffold,</hi> than the <hi>Throne:</hi> and therefore it muſt needs be more honourable (after the late Heroick Example of <hi>England</hi>) that the Judgements of God ſhould be execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in publick before all the world, than that they ſhould be ſtiffled in a Dungeon, or the Majeſty of them be leſs'ned by paltry private Aſſaſſinations, or poiſonings, acted upon <hi>Royall Tyrants</hi> and <hi>Offenders.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:112620:35"/>
                     <p>Even the practiſe of <hi>Scotland</hi> it ſelf, will furniſh us with Examples enough of this nature; where no leſs than fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of their Kings have been puniſhed with death; and the greateſt part of them by a <hi>ſolemn Iudiciall Proceeding:</hi> as it is ſet forth by <hi>Buchanan,</hi> their own Hiſtorian, who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms it to be, <hi>More Majorum,</hi> according to the cuſtome of their Anceſtors: So that of all other men in the world, this <hi>Scot Reſident,</hi> hath the leaſt reaſon to wonder at our Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital Proceeding againſt a Tyrant, as a thing never heard of before in the world, ſince it hath been (from all Antiquity) the common practice of his own Country.</p>
                     <p>Whereas, he farther alledgeth, the <hi>Parliment</hi>'s <hi>mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold reiterated Oaths, and their Covenants, with above an hundred Parlimentary Declarations and Proteſtations, to protect the King's Perſon and Poſterity,</hi> &amp;c. This muſt be underſtood, with that <hi>tacit Suppoſition,</hi> which is naturally included in all thoſe Oaths and Proteſtations, <hi>viz.</hi> That he do not by any enormous crimes and continued Acts of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, deveſt himſelf of his Kingly capacity. And in the <hi>Covenant</hi> it ſelf, as much as this comes to is implied by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable conſequence, the whole ſcope of it being qualified with this ſpecial clauſe <hi>[In the preſervation of Religion and Liberty]</hi> to ſhew, that if the King ſhould proceed ſo far, as to render himſelf an irreconcileable enemy to both, the Covenant did no longer oblige the Covenanters, in any relation to him; or his Poſterity.</p>
                     <p>But he ſaith, <hi>The Laws of</hi> England <hi>favour Kings above the Laws of all other Nations;</hi> and for this he alledges the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſiticall maxims uſed by Courtiers, <hi>Rex non moritur, Rex nulli facit injuriam:</hi> Whereto let us oppoſe others out of our old Laws more rationall and ſound; <hi>Non debet eſſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge major quiſquam in exhibitione Juris; minimus autem eſſe debet in judicio ſuſcipiendo, ſi peccat. Rex habet ſuperiores, Legem; per quam factus eſt Rex, &amp; Curiam ſuam,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Nihil aliud poteſt Rex, niſi id ſolum quod de Jure poteſt,</hi> ſay <hi>Bracton</hi> and <hi>Fleta.</hi> and whereas he is up again with his pious <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines</hi> in and about <hi>London,</hi> whoſe <hi>Declaration</hi> he much boaſts of in the behalf of the late <hi>Tyrant</hi> and his <hi>Cauſe;</hi> In Anſwer to this, he muſt give us leave to reply in ſuch a ſence
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:112620:35"/>as out own experiences have taught us; that thoſe whom he calls <hi>Divines,</hi> were the greateſt <hi>Carnaliſts, Formaliſts,</hi> and <hi>Fanaticks,</hi> that ever appeared in any Nation; <hi>Court para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites,</hi> Trumpets of Tyranny; the onely Patrons and Promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Slavery,</hi> both <hi>Spirituall</hi> and <hi>Tempporall.</hi> They were ſuch (as moſt of the ſame <hi>Tribe</hi> ever have been and are) men ignorant in the more neceſſary and ſolid parts of Learning (both <hi>Sacred</hi> and <hi>Civill</hi>) who make a Trade and Traffique of certain <hi>Set-forms,</hi> and <hi>maxims</hi> of <hi>Divinity;</hi> wherein be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Travell'd, as in a <hi>Road,</hi> they cannot out of their old way, but immediately they loſe themſelves and their ſences. If a <hi>Truth</hi> (though never ſo bright and glorious) come to claſh with any of thoſe <hi>trading notions</hi> which they call <hi>Orthodox,</hi> then immediately like the men of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> they grow ſtark mad, and can ſing no other Tune to all the world, but <hi>Great is their Diana.</hi> Therefore, In thoſe high and weighty Controverſies which ariſe concerning the Rights and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments of Commonweals and Kingdoms (where their motions are <hi>eccentricall</hi>) little regard is to be had to their fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gid Conceptions, where in they are wont, even in <hi>Luce meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dianâ, toto coelo err are;</hi> and in this particular it might be made good (contrary to their Affirmations and Invectives) even as clear as the Sun, <hi>According to the holy word of God; the Inſtinct of Nature; Right Reaſon; The Laws of all Nations,</hi> and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly of <hi>England;</hi> That <hi>Parliaments,</hi> or other <hi>Supream Aſſemblies,</hi> have a Power of Juriſdiction (both <hi>coercive</hi> and <hi>punitive</hi>) over their Kings, and of altering Forms of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, according to the Publique exigents and Conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of their reſpective Nations, In the meantime this <hi>Scot</hi> may do well, ſince he often quotes <hi>William Prynn,</hi> to conſult that great <hi>Scotiſer;</hi> in his Book entitled, <hi>The Soveraign power of Parliaments;</hi> as alſo his own Countriman <hi>Rutherford</hi> in his <hi>Lex, Rex:</hi> who will give him another Account, than the raw <hi>Pulpiteers</hi> of <hi>London.</hi> Next, he affirms, that the ſaying of our <hi>Saviour</hi> which commands the paying of Tribute to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> confirmeth and eſtabliſheth Lawfull Power. Herein we agree with him; For, though the means whereby that Power of the <hi>Caeſars</hi> was gained were unlawfull, and the manner of its <hi>Acquiſition</hi> unjuſt; yet it being once eſtabliſhed beyond the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:112620:36"/>controll of any Publique Power, and having all Authority ſeated within it ſelf, it immediately became lawfull by way of diſpenſation, having a right to the diſpenſing of Juſtice, and to the exerciſe of all Acts of Juriſdiction concerning privat and particular Perſons. But then (ſaith he) ſhould <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> have acquieſſed in the uſurped power of <hi>Abſolom,</hi> and <hi>Solomon</hi> in the power of <hi>Adonijah; Jehoiada</hi> in <hi>Athalia's,</hi> and the <hi>Machabees</hi> in the power of <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes.</hi> Alas, the caſe of theſe is far different; for neither <hi>Abſolom,</hi> nor <hi>Adonijah,</hi> were ever ſeated in a plenary poſſeſſion, nor had they been acknowledged Supream, as were the <hi>Caeſars;</hi> nor had the <hi>Jews</hi> made any recognition of <hi>Antiochus</hi> his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, nor did he ever bring them under a totall Subjugation, as afterwards did the <hi>Roman</hi> power, to whom they then paid a finall ſubmiſſion, though they refuſed it before to <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochus:</hi> As for that of <hi>Athaliah,</hi> we finde ſhe had a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion paid for no leſs than 6 years, though her power were uſurped; and one main reaſon why the people denied it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward was, becauſ ſhe had agrieved the whole Nation with her practiſes of Idolatry and Tyranny: for which cauſe, ſhe was lawfully depoſed and put to death in a full Aſſembly of the Princes and People. 2. <hi>Kings</hi> 11. after which, they redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the Government into its former courſe of ſucceſſion. Thus much we thought fit to anſwer, as to this particular: But what hath this <hi>Scottiſh Reſident</hi> to do to introduce theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of <hi>Abſolom, Adonijah,</hi> and <hi>Athaliah,</hi> as Arguments againſt us in <hi>England?</hi> They touch not the matter at all, there being as vaſt a diſproportion betwixt them and us, as betwixt light and darkneſs; for they were ſingle Uſurpers over the People; but here in <hi>England</hi> the People have recovered their own Rights, by ridding away an old Tyrannical Uſurpation.</p>
                     <p>He compares alſo the <hi>Religion</hi> that was under Kings in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> with the preſent, and ſaith that in the Kings time <hi>it ſhone as a Lamp, more clear then in any other Nation: But that now it is nothing like the religion profeſſed in</hi> Holland, <hi>nor indeed Religion it ſelf.</hi> What the ſtate or <hi>religion</hi> was in the Kings time, I ſuppoſe we need not now diſpute, it having been long ſince condemned, not only by our <hi>Presbyterians</hi> themſelves, but in the Iudgement alſo of Forain <hi>reformed Churches,</hi> as a
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:112620:36"/>profane <hi>medley</hi> of ſuperſtitious Innovations. And as to the preſent, though we glory not in an external pretended <hi>Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> (the great <hi>Diana</hi> of the Clergy, and wherein they place all religion, becauſe it makes for their profit) yet it bears a proportionable conformity to the mind of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the tenor fo his <hi>Goſpel,</hi> which teacheth us to gather <hi>Believers</hi> into Congregations by the power of the <hi>Word,</hi> and not force men promiſcuouſly into a pretended <hi>Church-relation</hi> by the power of the <hi>ſword,</hi> or commands and conſtitutions of any worldly <hi>Power.</hi> This, together with a prudent <hi>Toleration</hi> of different opinions, is the preſent ſtate of Religion in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> ſo that whoſoever takes a view of the practiſes of both Nations, will eaſily grant a conformity of profeſſion betwixt us, and our neighbours of the <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>He alledges farther, <hi>It would be more ſafe and profitable for the States, that</hi> England <hi>ſhould continue a</hi> Monarchy, <hi>than become a</hi> Republick, <hi>for that the increaſe of</hi> England <hi>in a free State would be the decreaſe of the other.</hi> See here, O ye peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>England,</hi> what a Confeſſion here is out of the mouth of the <hi>Common Enemy,</hi> of the poſſibility of that increaſe, both in wealth and honour, which our Nation may expect in the ſettled Form of a <hi>Free State,</hi> or <hi>Commonwealth.</hi> And if ſo, then by conſequence it follows, that all this ſtir for a <hi>Royal Family,</hi> and <hi>Monarchy,</hi> is not out of any reſpect to the increaſe of the publick weal, but only to ſatisfie the ambition of a ſingle <hi>Tyrant</hi> and his Followers. And rather than not be ſo ſatisfied, he here (by the mouth of his Orator, <hi>Mac-Don<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel</hi>) offers up the future intereſt and glory of <hi>England,</hi> as a prey unto the <hi>Dutch,</hi> in hope to allure them unto his party, for the reſtoring of him into a <hi>Tyranny:</hi> ſo that you ſee clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is a thirſt of Dominion and Revenge, not the people's benefit, that tranſports him in all his undertakings. It is here acknowledged by himſelf, that his own reſtitution will be a means to keep <hi>England</hi> from growing richer and greater; the fear whereof, he uſeth as an argument to provoke the jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie and emulation of <hi>Holland.</hi> The inference therefore is natural and eaſie, out of his own mouth; that the intereſt of himſelf, and <hi>family,</hi> is inconſiſtent with the increaſe, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation:</p>
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:112620:37"/>
                     <p>In the next place, he indeavors to darken the glory of God in our many wondrous ſucceſſes; ſaying, they are no good ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument to juſtifie a <hi>cauſe,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Turk</hi> hath had as great ſucceſſes as any. But what ever this <hi>Babler</hi> ſaith, we cannot be ſo ignorant of the good hand of God upon us, as to let thoſe glorious works of Providence, whereby he hath pleaded the Cauſe of this Parliament and Commonwealth, paſs under the common title of <hi>Fortune de la guerre;</hi> The <hi>Lord</hi> having cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on this marvellous work for time and place, with a concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of ſuch remarkable circumſtances, that the very enemies have at length acknowledged it to be <hi>digitus Dei,</hi> as did D. <hi>Hamilton</hi> (before his death) and others, who ſaw the ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out arm of God in the late defeat at <hi>Worceſter.</hi> We juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie not our <hi>cauſe</hi> by ſucceſſes; but only behold them as the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of Gods mercy and goodneſs, owning us in a juſt ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, againſt the enemies of himſelf and people. The <hi>Turks</hi> deſign was to propagate <hi>Tyranny</hi> in <hi>Chriſtendom;</hi> ours to pul it down. His, only to increaſe his own Dominion; ours, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt the Dominion of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> What he did, was by main ſtrength, multitudes, and help of human policy. What we have done, hath been by a deſpiſed remnant, inconſiderable, both for knowledg &amp; number, againſt all the wiſe and mighty men of this generation, who to their power &amp; wiſdom, have had ſo many great advantages from time to time, that the <hi>deciſion</hi> of every ſucceſs, in our behalf, hath been ſo manifeſtly written with the <hi>finger of God,</hi> that all muſt confeſs, it could be no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hand but his that did it: witneſs the great advantage the Enemy had of us at <hi>Naisby;</hi> the miraculous ſally at <hi>Dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin,</hi> with the many glorious defeats that followed in <hi>Ireland;</hi> the great deliverances wrought in 1648, when by a <hi>ſmall army</hi> divided into two handfuls, we with one part quieted <hi>South-Wales,</hi> and vanquiſht <hi>Hamiltons</hi> galiant army; and with the other part, ſuppreſſed the many numerous Inſurrections in <hi>Kent, Eſſex,</hi> &amp;c. Witneſs alſo that glorious deliverance (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all reaſon) given laſt year at <hi>Dunbar,</hi> when by a poor handful of ſick men, wearied out with watchings, hunger, and inceſſant marches in tedious weather, &amp; at length impounded within a narrow neck of Land, ſurrounded by the ſea, they did notwithſtanding (in the ſtrength of God) defeat the nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:112620:37"/>
                        <hi>Scottiſh Army,</hi> it being accommodated with all neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries and advantages, and one of the beſt accompliſht armies, that ever appeared in <hi>Scotland.</hi> Add to-theſe (omitting many other) the late memorable defeat at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> attended with a <hi>ſeries</hi> of many other wondrous ſucceſſes: and it is ſo much the more obſervable, in regard of that miraculous power of God upon the heaſts of the people, faſtning them to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, in a moſt notable time of trial, to the ſhameful con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation of this ſhameleſs <hi>Reſident,</hi> who had the impudence to affirm, that not the <hi>hundreth part,</hi> or (as he ſaith a little af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) not the <hi>thouſandth part</hi> of the people, <hi>but do cordially ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to the Royal Intereſt, and paſſionatly groan to be delivered from the prevailing party in</hi> England, as he is pleaſed to call the <hi>Parliament:</hi> whereas, all the time of the <hi>Scot</hi>'s <hi>King</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing among us (which was about 28 days) courting and wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the people with all manner of inſinuations, intreaties, and pretences, he was not owned by any conſiderable number of his <hi>old friends,</hi> or his new-reconciled Enemies of the <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian</hi> party. From all which particulars, (what ever other men may deem) we cannot but ſee the hand of God reached out unto us, for the upholding of this Government, in a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar manner, contrary to all the expectations and reaſonings oſ worldly wiſdom. Since the drying up of the <hi>red ſea,</hi> with the wonders that were wrought in Aegypt, and in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, never have there been more glorious appearances of Gods preſence, than among his people in <hi>England:</hi> And therefore, none but a profane heart will preſume ſo much to detract from the glory of theſe diſpenſations, as to rank them among the ordinary paſſages of a permiſſive, or <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence.</p>
                     <p>The laſt that we ſhall take notice of, is one of the principall arguments that he uſeth to hold the <hi>Dutch</hi> to his young <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi>'s party; hinting unto them by way of inſinuation, <hi>that no Nation is ſo ſubject to change as</hi> England; <hi>that the Earl of</hi> Warwick <hi>in</hi> 11 <hi>days,</hi> Edw. 4. <hi>in</hi> 20, <hi>and</hi> Hen. 7. <hi>in</hi> 1 <hi>day, ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively ſubdued the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Nation.</hi> Tis true, <hi>England</hi> hath received many a ſudden change, but never ſuch a change as now. Heretofore, the poor people toiled themſelvs, in ſhif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting one <hi>Tyrant</hi> out of the ſaddle to ſet up another; but
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:112620:38"/>now they have driven out, not only the <hi>Tyrant,</hi> but Tyranny it ſelf, and caſhiered not only a ſingle King, but all Kings for ever. It is an eaſie matter for particulars to ſupplant one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother in Government, becauſe the intereſt ſtands depoſited in a ſingle hand; but when the whole frame of Government is altered from what it was, and the intereſt of State lies diffu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the hands of the people, it is almoſt impoſſible to alter it again, without ſuch a tract of time, as may produce new diſpoſitions and opportunities for the effecting a new altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Beſides, it is very rarely obſerved in the whole courſe of Hiſtory, that ever <hi>Kingly Government</hi> was ſuddenly reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in any Country, after it had been once caſhiered by the people.</p>
                     <p>As for <hi>Robert Bruce,</hi> his recovery of all <hi>Scotland,</hi> 300 years ago, out of the hands of the Engliſh; you know it could not be effected as long as <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. lived; but advantages being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the infirmities, debaucheries, and civil broils of <hi>Edw.</hi> 2. the Scots made a ſhift to ſhake off the yoak; wherein they were more beholding to that <hi>Prince</hi>'s <hi>vanity,</hi> than the valour and vertue of their own Nation. And whereas he calls <hi>Ster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin</hi> the <hi>unconquered, and fatall Bulwark of</hi> Scotland, and tells us, that there they <hi>ſtopt the current of the Roman</hi> Victories; yet their own Hiſtorian <hi>Buchanan</hi> confeſſeth, that both <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. and 2. were poſſeſt of <hi>Sterlin</hi> by force of arms: and both their and our Hiſtorians will be able to relate in time to come how that the Commonwealth of <hi>England</hi> hath done more than <hi>Rome,</hi> and made another Conqueſt, not only of <hi>Sterlin,</hi> but far beyond it; which I dare be bold to ſecond with this <hi>Omen:</hi> That as <hi>Scotland</hi>'s happineſs will be promoted by a ſubjection to <hi>England;</hi> ſo now it is the deſign of God, for the better carrying on of his great work, and the good of that people, to bring them into an univerſal ſubmiſſion to the Laws and Government of the Engliſh Nation.</p>
                     <epigraph>
                        <q>— Nec ſit Terris <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltima Thule.</q>
                     </epigraph>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
